<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Knowledge Specialization VS Generalisation</title>
    <link href="/2023/08/19/speci/"/>
    <url>/2023/08/19/speci/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There has probably been no better time than now, to discuss this topic of </p><p>specialising knowledge on one or a handful of topics, </p><p>VS</p><p>generalising and branching out in many different topics,</p><p>because the access to information is unlimited, </p><p>and so investigating this distinction,<br>in light of the information revolution we’re experiencing,<br>and the infinite options we have,</p><p>has never been practically and intellectually more relevant.</p><h3 id="The-two-fundamental-aspects"><a href="#The-two-fundamental-aspects" class="headerlink" title="The two fundamental aspects:"></a>The two fundamental aspects:</h3><p>As you might know from previous posts, </p><p>the word “fundamental” and what it means, is almost intrinsic to my genes, so let’s start with exactly that.</p><p>There is an essential aspect of our comparison that needs addressing which is:</p><p>in what way&#x2F;metric, specifically, are we actually comparing knowledge specialization and generalization?</p><p>We can look at it from two fundamental broad angles and pose our comparison like this:</p><p>1st - Which one serves “economic” purposes better, Specialization or generalization? </p><p>2nd - Which one gets you closer to the truth, Specialization or generalization?</p><p>“Economic purposes” might seem fancier than it actually is,</p><p>But what I really mean is: any benefits that can come out of interactions in a market, </p><p>whether for the individual themselves who offers the interaction, or the consumer of that interaction in the market.</p><p>You might be asking, why those two categories, specifically ?</p><p>Well, those two are the most relevant and overarching, to answer the question in a meaningful way,</p><p>because it seems like when humans devote their energy to specialization of knowledge or generalization, </p><p>they try to optimize for one, or both of those two categories, in some deep way.</p><h3 id="Specialized-Economy-The-Fallible-Superpower"><a href="#Specialized-Economy-The-Fallible-Superpower" class="headerlink" title="Specialized Economy: The Fallible Superpower?"></a>Specialized Economy: The Fallible Superpower?</h3><p>It would be nieve, in mainstream consciousness, </p><p>to say that specialization is “not good” for human innovation, and&#x2F;or a “thriving&#x2F;growing” economy.</p><p>because it’s seems like people who have had their hands in practical day-day modern life&#x2F;work&#x2F;knowledge, </p><p>would know that a big reason the economy is functioning the way it is,</p><p>is because every task, skillset, or knowledge is atomised and specialised, for specific people to do.</p><p>But the idea that a “growing” economy due to specialization, reflexively &#x3D; a “good” economy, is just <em>one</em> way to look at the situation…</p><p>And although, a growing economy due to specialization, is reflexively and immediately identified as a “good economy”,</p><p>there is more to it than that we can say.</p><p>And in order to understand the other aspects of the situation, we need to understand what makes a “good” economy.</p><p>Establishing growth as not necessarily leading to a “good” economy:</p><p>Hang on with me, we’ll relate this idea to specialization soon enough.</p><p>So to continue on the growth thread,</p><p>If we deconstruct and rebuild the economy in our minds from scratch, and look at it from first principles,</p><p>we’ll discover very quickly that, whether an economy is “thriving” or “growing, is only <em>one</em> subset of the economy, and its “goodness”.</p><p>And although growth is important in a lot of aspects, and we need it, to assess our economic trajectory, abstractly,</p><p>but when we pay close attention, </p><p>we see that “growth” can <b>sometimes</b>, be completely detached from anything we would call a “good economy”.</p><p>Now don’t get me wrong, </p><p>I am not saying growth is detrimental,</p><p>all I am saying up to this point is that, let’s not forget that growth as a metric (which is sometimes portrayed as an untouched scripture), is not sufficient to call an economy “good”.</p><p>To strike a relevant example,<br>we can say that unjustified proxy wars, harmful-industrial complexes, and addictive material,</p><p>could actually be a hardcore growth driver for the economy,</p><p>but that would definitely not account for a “good” economy, in the holistic sense the of the term.</p><p>Because what is the purpose of an economic system really, if we think about it? </p><p>Its purpose is not growth as a detached metric (or GDP), </p><p>but it’s for people to serve each other, in the most “win-win” situation possible.</p><p>Every fruitful economic exchange contributes to “growth”, </p><p>but not every increase in “growth”, is made up of “fruitful” economic exchanges.</p><p>The first part of the sentence make us slip into believing the second part is true,</p><p>but as we showed, that’s not always the case.</p><h3 id="How-does-this-link-to-specialisation"><a href="#How-does-this-link-to-specialisation" class="headerlink" title="How does this link to specialisation:"></a>How does this link to specialisation:</h3><p>But hold on, why say all of these points about growth?</p><p>I don’t mean to get you lost at all with all this talk,</p><p>but the points I’ve been making about growth, link to this very deep critique of specialisation, that we have to be careful about, even when approaching day-day life.</p><p>Remember we said that growth can mean a good economy, but not necessarily?</p><p>Well, specialization makes it <b>more probable</b> for the “growth-is-detached-from-good” phenomena (let’s call it that from now on) to happen.</p><p>If I bring 20 people (specialised) who were asked to build a drone that damages or ends people’s lives,<br>to sell it and “grow”, </p><p>it’s easier for them to avoid, or even not see, the “guilt” of the job, than if it were one person doing it,</p><p>because one of them is just tightening the screws, </p><p>the other is working on the engine, and another person is working on the controller,</p><p>So it’s easier for them to bask in the pixels, rather than vividly see the “bad” bigger picture they’re about to make real.</p><p>So scaling that problem of specialising and atomising, up, can give rise to more of the “growth-detached-from-good phenomena”, </p><p>where growth, as the name suggests, is detached from the “goodness” of the economy, </p><p>because everyone responsible for that “bad” growth, </p><p>is <b>less likely</b> to see, or psychologically experience, let’s say, the bad sides they’re involved in, and stop it, as we stated in this example.</p><p>So humans specialising the system out of guilt, is a thing, in the case of <b>some</b> perverse incentives, like the examples we showed.</p><h3 id="Caveats-on-the-previous-ideas-recap-setting-the-limits"><a href="#Caveats-on-the-previous-ideas-recap-setting-the-limits" class="headerlink" title="Caveats on the previous ideas &#x2F; recap &#x2F; setting the limits:"></a>Caveats on the previous ideas &#x2F; recap &#x2F; setting the limits:</h3><p>I want to stress on the fact that the growth problem, and relating it to specialization,</p><p>is not to say specialization is to be abandoned for generalization (to be explored soon), or any other paradigm, for instance, </p><p>because specialization, as we probably alluded to earlier, is crucial to even begin to conceptualize wealth&#x2F;capital creation, as we know it.</p><p>However, this is more to set the stage for an improvement, or a caveat, towards the idea of specialization, </p><p>or division of “labor”, as it’s known in economics circles.</p><p>I guess to link the problem we mentioned to a higher form of philosophy,<br>from a metaphysical, moral, and individual&#x2F;personal perspective, </p><p>all I am trying to say is that specialization can <b>occasionally</b> dilute your morals, indirectly, </p><p>as it’s more difficult to actually see the bigger picture you’re operating under, and construct it in a clear way.</p><ol start="2"><li>Another caveat that’s perhaps also  important to note is that,</li></ol><p>There is a gradient where everything we  said about the specialization problem can be over-emphasised by someone.</p><p>The overemphasis can actualise sometimes, by looking at the “bigger picture” at every step of the way,<br>which is not actually “essential and might actually make it more difficult to understand something, as I might’ve portrayed it to be.</p><p>(perhaps it’s a personal preference to always bring things to the bigger picture, but I wanted to be objective and mention this point&#x2F;limitation, even though I always try to bring things to the bigger picture).</p><p>And this ability to kind of “ignore” the bigger picture is actually, ironically enough, why specialization is so efficient, </p><p>because if we always look at the bigger picture whenever we take a step, </p><p>we wouldn’t be able to even practically dive that deep into a piece of knowledge or skill.</p><p>But with all these things into consideration,</p><p>we need to be cognizant of all the nuances we have mentioned thus far, and be conscious of our “specialization” and what it could do.</p><p>This probably not as relevant to people as much as I think,</p><p>but from a practical perspective,</p><p>it’s definitely something to think about when trying to work under the guise of specialization.</p><h3 id="Truth"><a href="#Truth" class="headerlink" title="Truth:"></a>Truth:</h3><p>You would think that focusing on a specific discipline would get you even closer to “the truth”,</p><p>because it seems like we always attribute  “knowingness” to the people who are “experts” on a specific thing.</p><p>But there is one approach that perhaps</p><p>important to mention which is that,<br>humans don’t only learn things and describe them, </p><p>they also project their points of views to things, as well, So it’s a recursive cycle.</p><p>So one conclusion we can extract from the previous premise we laid out, in relationship to specialization,</p><p>is that a specialised person might actually project their point of view or their area of study to a phenomena, </p><p>and see it as a <b>sufficient</b> “truthful” explanation, even when it’s not a complete explanation.</p><p>Wars can be explained by psychologists as individuals in conflict, </p><p>Economists will tell you money is responsible for the wars.</p><p>Political scientists will tell you it’s all political figures fighting each other.</p><p>Sociologists will tell you it’s all about ideologies&#x2F;cultures.</p><p>and the list goes on…</p><p>Perhaps this is not a great accurate example, </p><p>but it makes clear the idea of the increased capability of specialised humans, to reduce the truth,</p><p>and&#x2F;or project their specialised views, as an effectively, <b>complete</b> one.</p><p>Paradox of knowledge: where the previous problem breaks down:</p><p>Now, I want to honestly say that </p><p>The problem of “specialization leading away from truthful general explanations”,</p><p>we presented above, Does seem to break down at some level.</p><p>And although it’s directionally correct, </p><p>it doesn’t seem to be a very accurate representation of the dynamics between specialization and truth, <b>as a whole</b>. </p><p>so let me explain this idea through a paradox,</p><p>that relates to the point we mentioned, </p><p>which can actually point exactly where the explanation&#x2F;accuracy breaks down, so we can understand and clarify it more.</p><h4 id="So-the-paradox-which-I-call-the-“paradox-of-specialisation”-is-that"><a href="#So-the-paradox-which-I-call-the-“paradox-of-specialisation”-is-that" class="headerlink" title="So the paradox (which I call the “paradox of specialisation” is that:"></a>So the paradox (which I call the “paradox of specialisation” is that:</h4><p>it seems like, <b>collectively</b>, specialized humans,</p><p>are indeed reaching more truthful, or at least more nuanced explanations about the world, as a whole,</p><p>because we have all these different informational points of views, especially in the modern era.<br>(here’s where our previous problem of “specialization leading away from truth” breaks).</p><p>However, it seems like, <b>individually</b>, each one of those specialised people is,  </p><p>reducing the world to their specialised lens, and by extension, moving away from “truthful”&#x2F;more nuanced general holistic explanations. (Here’s where our problem, and war example holds).</p><p>So keeping that limit of my truth idea, in the form of this paradox, </p><p>really gives more things to branch into, and think about regarding this topic.</p><h3 id="System’s-thinking-generalization"><a href="#System’s-thinking-generalization" class="headerlink" title="System’s thinking &amp; generalization:"></a>System’s thinking &amp; generalization:</h3><p>So now that we have a schema of biases&#x2F;problems&#x2F;paradox (sometimes subconscious) that can arise as a result of specialization,</p><p>We can look at the other side of the spectrum, to try to neutralize the <b>possible</b> problems with some kind of mechanism.</p><p>Now,<br>Reverting our attention to systems thinking,<br><b>alongside</b> a specialised lens is crucial to counteract the problems we mentioned.</p><p>I like to think of Systems thinking as the idea of thinking about the world as a whole interconnected system, with complex interactions.</p><p>And I know this sounds silly &amp; obvious, but our minds will usually project the “partial” explanation (specialised point of view), as an explanation to a whole phenomena, </p><p>without even consciously recognizing the other “systems” that are interconnected, and into play sometimes (like our war example). </p><p>Not necessarily knowing all of them, but recognizing they might be in action here,</p><p>and understanding which ones can be relevant in a specific context,<b> that can be outside the ones we are operating under.</b></p><p>And of course we’ll never know all the “systems” into play, in a certain phenomena,</p><p>since there is a space of the “unknown unknowns”, </p><p>but staying conscious of that interconnectedness, is crucial when approaching the problems of specialization, we mentioned.</p><p>The person working with the controller of that drone will say: </p><p>“mmmm, maybe this controller will affect a bigger system than the one I’m directly operating with, let me rethink this, systematically.”</p><p>The person explaining the war through human psychology will be like: </p><p>“Perhaps, wars are even more complex than I think, my explanation might explain part of the phenomena, but it probably has a lot of other systems deeply affecting it.”</p><p>The “complex” part in systems thinking is also important.</p><p>Understanding that specializations are mostly “reductions” of a system, </p><p>will actually open up more holistic solutions to the problems we are trying to solve.</p><p>This is not to say that we’re necessarily against specialisation, as we mentioned previously, </p><p>but it is a more holistic way of looking at the world, even through a specialised lens.</p><h3 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion:"></a>Conclusion:</h3><p>I do want to say that it seems as if I’m arguing with myself on such issues,</p><p>as it is really more of thinking out loud, rather than a clear prescription,</p><p>but I think there is use in thinking about these things, in the way we did, </p><p>and those topics can also always lead to useful branches of thought.</p><p>Having said this, there isn’t a better way to end than with this directional quote said by someone wiser than me,</p><p>that I think portrays a lot of the diplomatic (and perhaps confusing) back and forth, we tried to convey, </p><p>for both specialization and generalization:</p><p>“Specialize in skills, generalize in knowledge.”</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
      <category>Economics</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sorry…Your thoughts in the closet are almost worthless</title>
    <link href="/2023/07/08/thought/"/>
    <url>/2023/07/08/thought/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We usually deem our thoughts as well-established or well understood by ourselves, </p><p>long before we put them out there in the world (putting them out there &#x3D; ex. Writing down thoughts, talking&#x2F;explaining an idea).</p><p>but actually if you ponder that idea, it should be the exact opposite&#x2F;reverse of that.</p><p>Your thoughts need to be in some way, out there, to validate whether they’re actually well-understood or not.</p><p>I never realized this until I actively started writing and also engaging my challenging thoughts more with the outside world. </p><p>Sometimes I’ll think to myself: “ohh, this idea is very well-conceptualised in my mind, I genuinely understand it well.”</p><p>But it turns out that, as soon as person X I am discussing with, changes the phrasing of the idea in their own way, I get somehow lost when I think about it from that different angle.</p><p>The example might make it seem like I mean engagement, <b>only in a social way,</b></p><p>but when I say engagement (although we’ll delve more into that in a few moments), I don’t really mean something social, per se,</p><p>writing your thoughts is considered engagement, because your putting it into words rather than <b>leaving them as floating notions in the mind</b>, which is, really, the key insight here.</p><p>And that constant engagement will punch holes through your “well-conceptualised” ideas over and over again,</p><p>and that will make you realise that you haven’t thought of point X in a good way, or point Y haven’t been considered, or maybe you need to think about assumption Z more, etc.</p><h3 id="It’s-a-changeable-threshold"><a href="#It’s-a-changeable-threshold" class="headerlink" title="It’s a changeable threshold:"></a>It’s a changeable threshold:</h3><p>It would be a misleading emphasis if I said that this “lack of realisation&#x2F;perception of true understanding in the mind” doesn’t change across time.</p><p>What I mean by that is, if one hypothetically doesn’t engage their thoughts in the outside world at all, they’ll think they understand much more than they <b>actually</b> do.</p><p>But if someone engaged, let’s say, 10 times before, with time and with engaging the thoughts with the outside world, </p><p>they would be more able to be the “devil’s advocate” in their own mind, and simulate an outside world with time, if that makes sense.</p><p>So the more you put your thoughts out there, the more your mind will be able to <b>realistically</b> judge whether you actually understand something in your own mind, or it’s just a façade waiting to be destroyed.</p><p>So now that we established why a framework of “exposing” one’s thoughts is important to understand things deeply, </p><p>It’s time to answer the question, what “medium” should you expose your thoughts through? </p><p>And does the medium with which you “expose” your thoughts really matter?</p><h3 id="Different-mediums-of-“putting-your-thoughts-out-there”"><a href="#Different-mediums-of-“putting-your-thoughts-out-there”" class="headerlink" title="Different mediums of “putting your thoughts out there”:"></a>Different mediums of “putting your thoughts out there”:</h3><p>There is a widely accepted myth that actually categorises people on what their “learning style” is.</p><p>And the myth will manifest itself by people saying things like: “I am a visual learner, I don’t <b>really</b> ‘learn’ by reading&#x2F;writing.”</p><p>or something like: “I like to listen to text being read, rather than consume it visually or read it.”</p><p>But I take a different route.</p><p>Operating and jumping on all possible grids of learning is really the optimal solution to understand things deeply.</p><p>And although varied methods of engaging with thoughts&#x2F;learning, is not a strictly necessary condition to actually learn something, </p><p>on top of our previously mentioned principles of exposing thoughts, it’s a great litmus test to validate understanding deeply.</p><p>Reading requires a relatively slow process of thinking, and there is irreplaceable usefulness in that slowness of thinking towards understanding.</p><p>Writing about something will teach you how to ask the right question about it, and express chaotic information, concisely.</p><p>Speaking will incrementally build your immediate intuitions about a topic.</p><p>Listening and paying attention to your interpretations will teach you how much your emotions are part of the knowledge you have.</p><p>Real-life application of knowledge will test your memory&#x2F;integration of that knowledge with the real world.</p><p>The “learning style” myth will reduce all these relatively exclusive qualities of different mediums, </p><p>into a deception that one of them should be “preferred” or “chosen”.</p><p>And, really, I say it’s a myth because limiting the possible mediums of learning&#x2F;challenging thoughts (ex. I don’t like to read), </p><p>is fundamentally a changeable habit that is worth cultivating, rather than a set-in-stone “style”.</p><h3 id="Limits-to-our-approach"><a href="#Limits-to-our-approach" class="headerlink" title="Limits to our approach?"></a>Limits to our approach?</h3><p>The most realistic and logical approach towards our aforementioned tenets (and anything else really),<br>is to actually acknowledge their limits and when not to use them,</p><p>To, in turn, genuinely understand where they can be most beneficial.</p><p>Now, Because we have, indeed, talked about how the principles can aid one in understanding deeply, </p><p>but the further question to ask is: are they universal principles that should always be enacted when understanding anything&#x2F; any topic?</p><p>To answer the question, it’s good to explicitly state the main assumption we made in everything we said until this point,<br>which is <b>wanting to understand deeply.</b></p><p>Since we have limited time as humans, we can’t, and don’t even often have the desire, to understand <b>everything deeply</b>.</p><p>People use cars all the time, for instance, but that doesn’t mean there is a deep desire and enthusiasm to understand them deeply.</p><p>So really the most practical and “meta” approach to act upon our model, is to choose your battles&#x2F;topics, so to speak, </p><p>to when to put the model fully in action, or when to half-heartedly pull it up.</p><p>so applying the principles in every topic one is trying to approach&#x2F;understand, is an “idealistic” rather than a “realistic” approach, </p><p>that will often end up draining one’s energy from the, perhaps, more important things.</p><p>Although it might be worth mentioning that my personal approach is to have this as a general philosophy, because I just love exploring everything deeply so much,</p><p>but I am stating the limitation and how that can be possibly misaligned, sometimes.</p><p>To drive this point home, and put everything in context, </p><p>let’s think about this diagram, in which it illustrates our approach to understanding ideas,<br>and how it also relates to our last point.</p><p>Although I don’t think this illustration is a very good and clear representation of the ideas in an accurate manner, it might just be a rough random reminder to just keep it in mind:<br><img src="/img/und.jpg"></p><p>(One might think this needs to be in this order, but the order is really a random construction to give an example).</p><h3 id="Bird’s-eye-view-Conclusion"><a href="#Bird’s-eye-view-Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Bird’s eye view&#x2F;Conclusion:"></a>Bird’s eye view&#x2F;Conclusion:</h3><p>The bird’s eye view on all the things we said is that, at the heart of it, the model&#x2F;approach we presented is an attainable habit worth cultivating. </p><p>Constantly knocking the door on our thoughts&#x2F;understandings with <b>exposure to things “outside of ourselves”</b>, through different varieties of angles&#x2F;mediums, </p><p>is <b>one</b> way to go about it, and to really see whether the energy we put into trying to understand something ,“with ourselves”, has been really transferred into something real, or has been transferred to a “fake” type of energy&#x2F;fake perception, waiting to be destroyed.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Psychology/Self-reflection</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Is Technology a proxy for progress?</title>
    <link href="/2023/05/29/tech/"/>
    <url>/2023/05/29/tech/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This question of Whether technologies actually lead to progress is something that is often taken for granted or overlooked.</p><p>As technologies are extremely close to us in everyday life, the answer to the question might seem super clear, but there are super interesting philosophic considerations that might give us deep insights on the topic as a whole, and our question, as well.</p><p>This might be one of those questions where we need to spend an entire article with every word, like what is technology, what is progress, really ?</p><p>This question is the ultimate example of, as the cliché goes, “the journey is more important than the destination” (i.e. final answer).</p><p>In order to even scratch the surface of the question we need to actually understand why do technologies even emerge, in the first place ?</p><h3 id="Technologies-Definitions-and-emergence"><a href="#Technologies-Definitions-and-emergence" class="headerlink" title="Technologies: Definitions and emergence:"></a>Technologies: Definitions and emergence:</h3><p>A technology is a lot of the times described (at least in our context) as a methodology of applying human insights and knowledge into the environment, and coming up with tools to serve different purposes.</p><p>I tend to take a bit of a different route than this definition, a more fundamental one, perhaps.<br>I think a technology, at the most basic&#x2F;abstract level, is really: a replicable control mechanism of the environment, and&#x2F;or interactions in that environment, for a specific purpose.</p><p>For example, cars are a way to control the distance variable for humans and get to places faster.</p><p>Phones manipulate information and are one way to control communication between humans more. If I can communicate only when close-by to someone, I don’t have much control over the ways of communication, but if I invent a phone, I have more power over the way I can communicate to fellow man.</p><p>The latter definition I mentioned has within it the reasons why we actually apply knowledge to come up with technologies (i.e. to control variables at our disposal), which is why I tend towards it more. </p><p>And we seek and try to look for those controllable variables by applying knowledge, science, experience, etc.  (which is implied in the former&#x2F;first definition I mentioned).</p><p>It might seem very weird to perceive technologies in this way, but the reason why I put it this way is because it will make the answer to our question even easier to understand.</p><p>We might be getting ahead of ourselves here, but let’s just give a brief sneak-peak on where our answer might be going, specifically, in relationship to the definition so we don’t forget the point.</p><p>What we have come to realize is that “control” of the environment, which is done by technologies, might <b>sometimes</b> be a deceiving appearance. </p><p>What happens sometimes is that we just, cleverly, and without knowing it, move the things we can’t control somewhere else we don’t see, rather than actually control the original problem, holistically.</p><p>A very proximal example in today’s world includes Social Media:</p><p>The invention of Social Media platforms was an invention for people to communicate, but Social Media created a whole package of social problems that weren’t considered, which one can think of as moving the problem of communication, or shifting it to the psychological&#x2F;sociological realm. </p><p>Which really means that the “lack of control” that was present, was merely moved to another domain, that itself requires control, if that makes sense.</p><h3 id="Interesting-philosophical-tangent"><a href="#Interesting-philosophical-tangent" class="headerlink" title="Interesting philosophical tangent:"></a>Interesting philosophical tangent:</h3><p>Not to stray away too much, but there is another interesting idea we can link to our idea of control.</p><p>In his book, problems of a sociology of Knowledge, Max Scheler argued for the case that domination and control of one’s surroundings, <b>and self</b>, was actually the crux of the European Enlightenment period, as its popularly known.</p><p>What he argued was that all the ideas of Enlightenment, emerged for a will to dominate and control the surroundings, as well as, the human subject or the self.</p><p>The surroundings part shaped itself by  building tools and technologies using scientific knowledge, that can help man get more control over the external scene.</p><p>The self or the human subject part shaped itself by moving away from things that control man’s existence, such as the rise of individualism, and that “eliminated” external control of man, which in turn gave more control over oneself.</p><p>Scheler, takes this argument one step further and says that this has actually leaked itself into, interestingly enough, the state, as well.</p><p>Although it’s a bit of a reductionist point of view to look at the Enlightenment period through this lens only, but it’s pretty useful to boil down some common factors between technologies in this way. </p><h3 id="Recapping"><a href="#Recapping" class="headerlink" title="Recapping:"></a>Recapping:</h3><p>So now that we have a somehow random perspective on what technologies are and have an idea on the basic assumption humans might have when different technologies are produced.</p><p>So now comes the question, does this method of controlling the environment lead to “progress” ?</p><p>This will lead us to actually go on another brief trip in exploring what people usually mean by “progress”. And then we can reconstruct our question more clearly by being on the same page with terminologies and their emergence.</p><h3 id="“Progress”"><a href="#“Progress”" class="headerlink" title="“Progress”:"></a>“Progress”:</h3><p>Progress, as far as I see it, is almost always fundamentally used interchangeably with “change”, <b>except</b>, that, usually, there are good connotations intended with that change, when people use the word “progress” (whatever subjective “good” the speaker is attaching to it).</p><p>One other thing we have to acknowledge is that the concept of progress is fundamentally a relative one. You can’t have “progress” (or change) without measuring it against something, first.</p><p>You need to have a threshold or a measure to actually make sense of something like “progress”.</p><p>Now, the following two “metrics”, we can say, are the ones that are often-times used as approximate measures for progress (they can be a lot of the times subconsciously assumed):</p><ol><li><p>They’ll look towards the past, and compare it with present, so that’s one measure.</p></li><li><p>In our specific context, at least, the second measure on top of that is the amount of proximal “suffering” of the people, compared to the past, of course (the less suffering&#x2F;more comfort, the more the “progress”, according to that measure).</p></li></ol><h3 id="Reconstructing-the-question"><a href="#Reconstructing-the-question" class="headerlink" title="Reconstructing the question:"></a>Reconstructing the question:</h3><p>So now that we know the game when it comes to our definitions, let’s ask our question, does technology always lead to progress ?</p><p>Let’s tackle the question by proposing two opposing hypothetical views , and the we can construct where the truth probably lies and why.</p><p>View 1:<br>“Technology leads us to places we never thought we would be in as humans, it has lifted a lot of people out of poverty, and helped people live more comfortable lives. So I am all for technology !”</p><p>View 2:<br>“Technology is a great way to improve quality of life for humanity and purport achievements, However, we have to understand each technology and see what are their long-term externalities.”</p><p>So as we probably somehow alluded to before, view 2 is closer to being more correct,<br>here is why:</p><p> <b>1</b>) I think View 2 is an attempt to look at the whole picture, rather than a pixel. </p><p>One can’t deny that technologies lead to “progress”, or as the measure we set towards progress, “reduces suffering”, but to think that it’s the entire full picture, is a shallow way to look at the world.</p><p>Progress, or “lack of suffering” can be easily off-set in the future by socialising risks that might add up to be a net-negative, which eventually cancels out all the “progress” that certain people witnessed (assuming we define progress based on the measures we set forward).</p><p>A good example of this is leaded fuel.</p><p>When leaded fuel, which was used for vehicles, (which we can hypothetically think of as a technology) made it to the markets in the 1920’s,</p><p>It was increasing vehicles efficiency and everything was great for the people at the time. But years later, lead was discovered in people’s blood, and it was causing all sorts of health and intellectual problems in the world.</p><p>Perhaps this is an extreme example, but hopefully it shows us how we can think that something “can reduce the suffering”, or “lead to progress” (no pun intended), when in fact it can very much push the “suffering” to another domain, or in another time, and that might precipitously cause existential risks or even collapse.</p><p><b>2)</b> The world is extremely interconnected, anything we try to do affects everything else, to a degree. We have to be cognizant of , and try to understand, the high-order effects that we don’t see in the present, when we build technologies or do anything for that matter, as history has proved time and time again.</p><p>In an interconnected complex world, control is an illusion, to a degree. Since the world is interconnected and complex in every way possible, what we do sometimes is we displace the problem somewhere else we don’t visibly see, rather than solve it with “technology”, as we might think.</p><p>Of course, the degree to which the other problem is going to be more of a “pain”, is something up for debate, and asking to what degree and why, are the right questions to ask.</p><h3 id="Random-directions-at-tackling-such-issues"><a href="#Random-directions-at-tackling-such-issues" class="headerlink" title="Random directions at tackling such issues:"></a>Random directions at tackling such issues:</h3><p>Solving issues like the risks of exponential technologies, is multi-faceted and has all sorts of directions to tackle. </p><p>We can’t have people weighing societal risks of exponentially increasing technologies, when the Socioeconomic (with an emphasis on the Economic side) incentives are all pointed towards the direction of profit no matter what (“maximize the profits, socialize the risks” type of model).</p><p>It might also seem like “view 2” we discussed is really purporting a “slowing down” of technologies, but it’s much deeper than that.</p><p>It’s appealing to what is possible.</p><p>If we <b>can</b>, to a degree, predict the risks of man-made technologies, <b>if we take the extra miles and measures while building them and refining them</b>, and we do know that they actually have risks, then that possibility should be a good enough reason for the discussion to be had on our approach towards technologies, and to assess the benefits of society, rather than focus on the very close-by game-theoretic advantages we might enjoy.</p><p>This is, to a degree, easier said than done, as a shift towards building Human-values conscious technologies requires whole socioeconomic systems (as alluded to) to change its approach, to a degree.</p><p>Which in turn is an extremely difficult problem to solve and think about, which I’ll hopefully try to think about and write about more.</p><p>I want to take some time to say that really what we provided is not even a close trial to a full “solution”, but it’s rather to shed light on the issues and what the solutions might remotely look like.</p><h3 id="Meta-lesson-conclusion"><a href="#Meta-lesson-conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Meta-lesson&#x2F;conclusion:"></a>Meta-lesson&#x2F;conclusion:</h3><p>We saw that “progress” is really a deep concept that perhaps requires more thought than it is accredited with. </p><p>One thing we can extract from this is that, perhaps contrary to common belief, technologies are seldom “Black” or “White”, really (like a lot of other things).</p><p>But in order to shift it towards the “Benign&#x2F;good” side of things, we need to understand how it can give rise harmful consequences (sometimes as side-effects), and shift the approach to technologies to be more salutary, to the degree that that’s possible.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>The underestimated Principle: A new way of thinking</title>
    <link href="/2023/05/01/anew/"/>
    <url>/2023/05/01/anew/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="A-new-way-of-thinking"><a href="#A-new-way-of-thinking" class="headerlink" title="A new way of thinking ?"></a>A new way of thinking ?</h3><p>When people try to understand or plan something,<br>it’s usually done by understanding what a thing is (let’s call this property A), rather than understanding what that thing is <b>not</b> (let’s call this property B).</p><p>Now this sounds like silly, because “what a thing is not”  is literally everything else, that is not the thing itself (that’s not A).<br>So how is this useful to think about ?</p><p>But what I have come to realize is that<br>in the non-physical concepts, or abstract notions, or philosophies,<br>the line between the thing is, and what the thing is not, becomes sometimes extremely difficult to draw (example coming up), at least consciously.</p><p>And the thing about understanding what a thing is <b>not</b>, is to really understand the limits of a concept or idea. Because when you understand the limits of something, you can grasp the reach of its consequences, whether practically in your life, or philosophically with a specific idea.</p><h3 id="Meaning-of-life-Example"><a href="#Meaning-of-life-Example" class="headerlink" title="Meaning of life: Example."></a>Meaning of life: Example.</h3><p>A good example of this is when some people are asked about their purpose or the meaning of life. </p><p>People will sometimes declare notions that they don’t understand what they are <b>not</b>, and examples include: <b>experiencing</b> is the meaning of life, or being happy is the meaning of life.</p><p>So if we look at this with the lens of our principle, we see that what an “experience” is not, is something that’s not clear, because everything that humans conceive of is an experience in and of itself, if that makes sense.</p><p>And that will, by extension, enlighten us with the idea that the limits towards that meaning are ‘vague’, for a lack of a better word. </p><p>And as we said previously, as soon as we <b>don’t</b> understand the limits of an idea&#x2F;plan&#x2F;meaning, that informs us that the consequences of this purpose (experience or being happy) will probably not make a difference, on its own, as a meaning, because there is literally nothing that is not an “experience”, for instance.</p><p>so it becomes less meaningful when we look at from this angle.</p><h3 id="Where-the-importance-lies"><a href="#Where-the-importance-lies" class="headerlink" title="Where the importance lies:"></a>Where the importance lies:</h3><p>This principle, I think, is not applicable in every context of human thought or way of thinking, but this principle becomes much more important in very practical, actionable contexts, like the examples we previously mentioned (ex. the meaning of life, future-plans, etc.)</p><p>Because it’s very easy to deceive ourselves with devoid concepts that we think are really “meaningful” on their own, when with close thought, and approaching from different angles, they turn out to be less meaningful than we have thought.</p><h3 id="Applied-to-plans"><a href="#Applied-to-plans" class="headerlink" title="Applied to plans:"></a>Applied to plans:</h3><p>This sometimes happens when people plan, as well.</p><p>Sometimes people will state a very general plan, that is really not that meaningful with closer investigation, like: I want to learn “something” next year, or I want to make money this month. But when we heed those notes&#x2F;plans, on their own, they are really not that consequential or purposeful because it’s not clear what they are not, as there are uncountable ways to “make money” or “learn something”.</p><p>Obviously, a general plan supplied with other specific ones that <b>limit</b> the goal to something doable (ex. I want to make money by doing specifically x and y), is usually the practical and accurate way to do it, which is what most people do, but what our fallacy applies to, is when people declare a general plan, <b> on its own.</b></p><p>This example is not the most realistic one because most people do have specific plans, to a degree, but I hope this “extreme” example makes the point more direct.</p><h3 id="Conclusion-Meta-lesson"><a href="#Conclusion-Meta-lesson" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion &#x2F; Meta-lesson:"></a>Conclusion &#x2F; Meta-lesson:</h3><p>The meta-level lesson in here is that one has to understand that sometimes, stressing and pondering on the way of thinking about something, can be as equally important as seeking brand new information on a topic.</p><p>Slightly different Repetition (which is sometimes underestimated), from different angles, can be good mental gymnastics for trying to rationalize ideas, and can give completely new insights on a plan&#x2F;idea.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Psychology/Self-reflection</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Management of the most valuable (Time)</title>
    <link href="/2023/04/02/time/"/>
    <url>/2023/04/02/time/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s pretty safe to say that time management is the ultimate over-arching skill that penetrates every endeavour one is trying to reach. Everything requires time, and managing that time will automatically give you a default starting advantage over anything you’re trying to achieve.</p><p>I would like to start-off by saying, that the thing that took me the most time to figure out (and still does), is identifying the order&#x2F;sequence of “doing” and “planning”. Like what comes first, does or should planning precede action, or does&#x2F;should action sometimes come first, and shape the plan along the way ? and the answer is really not obvious when you look at the uncertainty and ever-changing conditions of life.</p><p>It’s not obvious to me how relevant this question is to time management, but it seems like time management is fundamentally a dynamic between plans and actions, in the background of the finiteness or limit of a human being’s time. </p><p>So let’s begin by trying to answer the question, and I’ll start-off with an illustration I drew that will make things much easier to understand throughout the answer:</p><h3 id="Building-the-model-from-scratch"><a href="#Building-the-model-from-scratch" class="headerlink" title="Building the model from scratch:"></a>Building the model from scratch:</h3><p><img src="/img/dra.jpg"></p><p>The first thing to establish is that this framework is really a general description on <b>how we act</b>, rather than <b>how it should be</b> in every context. Obviously, this semi-informs how things should be in some regard, but it’s not at all exhaustive. </p><p>Now, let’s break it up, what I mean by meaning is really the vague general master plan we have towards the approach to different things in life. That is not to say that it’s explicit and clear in everything we do, but we usually have some meaning or purpose that informs our objectives and actions, at least when we do things rationally, which, I believe, is not always the case.</p><p>An example of that would be when people go to university, or when one starts a business, one purpose or meaning is to provide a descent life financially (along with other meanings, of course), without reference to any specific details on how that’s going to get done.</p><p>Now the second pillar we had was the objectives part, which is informed by the meaning, but objectives are usually more specific or practical. We saw in the previous example that meaning&#x2F;purpose is to have a financial backing, for instance, now, the objective would be how you come to do that through. Are you going to be an accountant through going to university, an artist, an academic, or a freelancer. Some kind of specific <b>Plan</b> generation usually happens at this stage.</p><p>Before moving on to the action, note that a purpose doesn’t require you to have an extensive plan, initially, the meaning might even be a mere intuition, but the objectives stage is usually when one sets a plan. And this fact tells us that as one progresses with a plan and is trying to fulfill a bunch of other meanings as well, “objectives” can decouple from the “meaning” sometimes, which is an interesting time management side note we can think about.</p><p>The third pillar would be action phase, which is usually the time when one implements all the ideas they had in mind. </p><p>As we see in the illustration, there is a constant feedback between the objectives and actions, and that’s due to the uncertainty of life and flaws in our expectations. One might set objectives, but as soon as one starts acting, they change x, y, etc. in their objectives. </p><p>If we localize where the time management argument fits in this paradigm, we see that the time management problem emerges somewhere between the objectives-actions phase.</p><p>What I will say before moving on, is that this whole process is not necessarily conscious. A lot of the times people actually extract their meaning from conventional societal norms (or some other reason) without consciously going through it, which is, interestingly enough, one of the functions of society, because one simply doesn’t have enough wisdom, at least initially.</p><p>So approaching the problem of time management while keeping in mind our localization and diagnosis through the model, is key when trying to solve the problem, because it accounts for all the clear variables in the playfield, as far as we can see them, at least.</p><p>Like all models, the descriptions we talked about above doesn’t fully describe all approaches we have towards achieving things.</p><p>So to extract every insight we could from our flawed model, reversing it and observing what explanation can come out (as we see in the illustration) is one way to understand how we approach the world even more.</p><h3 id="“random”-mode"><a href="#“random”-mode" class="headerlink" title="“random” mode:"></a>“random” mode:</h3><p>So random mode is really applicable when life presents an opportunity all of a sudden sometimes, the action happens and then planning is shaped while the action is being done.</p><p>In that case, our regular meaning-objective-action model is not really accurate, and it becomes quite disorganized, for lack of a better word.</p><p>In a practical case of “random mode”, if one keeps working without having some idea of the meaning&#x2F;purpose or without objectives eventually, it might work for some while, and perhaps it’s needed for exploiting sudden opportunities that life gives us sometimes, but it will probably end up translating to burn-out from that action (or translate to other psychological forms), if the other two elements don’t eventually show up.</p><p>It’s worth mentioning one more thing, which is that going by and accepting the disorder of  “random mode” is less true for some people than others, because it depends on temperaments and metrics of personality, things like openness to experience and risk-averseness.</p><h3 id="Linking-it-back-to-time-management"><a href="#Linking-it-back-to-time-management" class="headerlink" title="Linking it back to time management:"></a>Linking it back to time management:</h3><p>Having mentioned all of this framework, I think that before setting any rules for time management, it’s good to be cognizant of all the things we mentioned, to have some kind of consciousness towards the different variables that weigh into this kind of calculation of time management.</p><p>Now that we have some insights on the background of our actions and endeavours, it would be good to mention a few principles that can make us optimize for “time management”, in light of this foundation.</p><h3 id="1-Plan-in-short-term-segments-first"><a href="#1-Plan-in-short-term-segments-first" class="headerlink" title="#1: Plan in short-term segments, first."></a>#1: Plan in short-term segments, first.</h3><p>So we said that after you have your meaning settled, objectives and planning come next. And this principle here is really related to the objectives part and how to approach it.</p><p>I think that, initially, planning in short-term segments is really optimal for translating plans into action. Let’s try to think about why that might be the case:</p><ol><li>When you plan in shorter segments (daily&#x2F;weekly), you have less chance of an on-going unnecessary change of plans that can slow you down,  because the further a goal is across time(ex.monthly&#x2F;yearly), the less accurate your prediction to achieve it will probably be (at least initially), and the less the accuracy, the more unnecessary change in plans, which makes it more difficult to execute the plan consistently and psychologically.</li></ol><p>So if we take an example of learning a programming language, if I say that I’ll work on problems in that programming language for 2 hours everyday, then there is a low chance of me bailing out of that commitment (assuming I have a well-established meaning, etc.) because it’s crystal clear and is very much a psychologically achievable goal.</p><p>However, if I say I’ll master learning the programming language at the end of the month (long-term goal), then the “unnecessary change” will haunt me, for the reasons we mentioned previously, and that approach of a “misplan” and unneeded change over and over again, will lead to different cascade events that will affect “time management”, and getting things done.</p><ol start="2"><li>Another reason why it’s more benign to plan more proximally, which we alluded to, is because the daily&#x2F;short-term plans seem more psychologically achievable for a person than the monthly ones, for example, and that thing itself will cause the person to get on the task more, rather than procrastinate it or leave it all-together because it seems so heavy or psychologically daunting.</li></ol><p>Now all of that is not to say that one’s plans should always be short-ranged, and with no deadlines, but what I am saying is that starting off with a short-term plan and then understanding the closely-related variables more, and afterwards, moving on to plan on a long-term is much more plausible to build a better sustainable framework of getting things done.</p><p>It’s a more achievable mission to have a bottom-up approach rather than a top-down approach, which means that, starting to understand all the close-range variables and plans, and then moving on to more distal or farther away plans is a rational and practical position to take from a time management perspective (keep in mind the out-of-norm “random mode” we mentioned, as these things we mentioned don’t always apply in every context).</p><h3 id="2-Set-“x”-amounts-of-introspective-problems-to-solve-every-week"><a href="#2-Set-“x”-amounts-of-introspective-problems-to-solve-every-week" class="headerlink" title="#2: Set “x” amounts of introspective problems to solve every week:"></a>#2: Set “x” amounts of introspective problems to solve every week:</h3><p>This one seems completely out of the blue, I mean we already solve problems everyday by default, however, the part I am stressing here is really the conscious effort of identifying a certain amount of personal&#x2F;introspective problems to solve every week.</p><p>The reason being that this attitude of picking things you want to change, will allow you to catch the small “sneak-in” problems that snowball themselves into obstacles, without being noticed.</p><p>You’ll be surprised how many issues&#x2F;problems go unchecked and affect the “efficiency” of achieving, without us noticing them. And the principle we proposed will, on a long enough frame, allow you to gradually remove things that have this feature.</p><p>And the reason why I say introspective is to stress that this doesn’t mean that they should be difficult or hard-to-solve problems, I am really talking about even the small things like waking up as soon as the alarm rings, or less breaks during exercise, for instance.</p><p>Another thing that this approach will definitely allow for, is it’ll build a feedback loop between you and your weaknesses, if that makes sense, because if you keep identifying problems (which is the first possible area of weakness because it’s a somehow a skill), and then solve them, or try, at least,(which is the second possible area of weakness), you’ll have an existence proof on where you’re weaknesses lie, constantly. </p><p>Obviously, solutions to those problems will not always work out from the first trial, but whether the thing is solved or not, the process will probably teach you somethings about yourself in relationship to time management, and other domains of life as well.</p><h3 id="3-Think-realistically-not-symbolically"><a href="#3-Think-realistically-not-symbolically" class="headerlink" title="#3: Think realistically not symbolically:"></a>#3: Think realistically not symbolically:</h3><p>Before we explain the principle here, I want to stress that thinking in symbols, or thinking symbolically, is really a wide topic that is discussed in rationality and psychology circles, and it’s not necessarily an “incorrect” way to think in every context, and is sometimes seen as an integral part of how we think and try to make sense of things as humans.</p><p>Without delving into symbolic thinking and defining it extensively, let’s start by taking an example of the scenario that comes to my mind when I think about this principle:</p><p>in the context of time management: if we imagine a person who works, and studies in university at the same time, thinking “symbolically” would be equivalent to something like this: “I don’t really have time to work on ‘x’ or ‘y’, because I am juggling between those two main things.”</p><p>So the symbol here is: “I Work and study at the same time.”</p><p>And the idea of a symbol can be stretched out by the person to irrelevant situations, and might repress other side things one might’ve wanted to do, whether consciously or subconsciously.</p><p>On the other hand, the realistic approach here would be something like:<br>“Calculating how many hours I have during the week and objectively seeing how much time each task takes.”<br>Or<br>“Whether the workload&#x2F;studyload changes during the week so I can work on other things.”<br>Or<br>“What habits can I change to gain more time for my other tasks, maybe I need to wake up earlier and finish up the side work, etc.”</p><h3 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion:"></a>Conclusion:</h3><p>At this point, we have built a somehow relevant intuition, and proposed some principles, and to put the cherry on the top, so to speak, let’s move on to a conclusive reminder that, as simple as it seems, was quite enlightening to me when thinking about this framework, and that is the fact that the week has almost <b>118</b> awake hours. So our most valuable asset is quite generous, if we approach it with a mindset that gives its real value.  </p>]]></content>
    
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>What is Economics and Money?</title>
    <link href="/2023/03/06/money/"/>
    <url>/2023/03/06/money/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="Economics-as-a-cycle"><a href="#Economics-as-a-cycle" class="headerlink" title="Economics as a cycle:"></a>Economics as a cycle:</h3><p>Economics strikes me sometimes as a somehow misrepresented field, in the sense that sometimes it’s presented as a mere “description” of the acts of an economizing man, if you like, without stressing on the interconnectedness or the interchangeability of the descriptions (examples coming up). And economizing man here really means everything that comes out when human beings deal with scarce resources&#x2F;services. </p><p>Now having said that, concepts and constituents in an Economic explanation can be more precisely illustrated, I think, as a cycle rather than a separate description of things, with a lot of the constituents of the cycle being the same thing, but looked at from different angles, and at different times, if that makes sense.</p><p>A small example is that sometimes we hear things like supply is the amount of a resource or service that is being provided in a market. And demand is the willingness of individuals to gain a service or a resource at a given price.<br>Now the definitions are accurate in one regard, however, if we take one step back, we see that supply and demand are fundamentally the same thing looked at from different angles.</p><p>Supply and demand are both reflections of the scarcity of a service&#x2F;good. If you have high “demand”, then you’re essentially describing the scarcity of that service, <b>relative to the number of agents that find utility in it </b>. If you have low supply, you’re essentially also describing the scarcity of a service&#x2F;good, <b>relative to the number of agents interested in it.</b></p><p>Now, these concepts are useful to use as “two separate things” because it can give us a distinction and help us understand the source of scarcity, if you like. if I use the word supply, then one would instantly understand that I am talking about scarcity from the perspective of production rather than the consumer’s (ex. low supply of bananas, means the production is not able to meet the number of people who want bananas). </p><p>If I use high demand, one would realize I am talking from the perspective of the consumer&#x2F;buyer (ex. high demand for bananas, means the number of people who want bananas have exceeded the production number).</p><p>Contrast the two examples and you’ll hopefully realize how they’re the same thing looked at from different angles.</p><p>Another illustration we can show of our cycle analysis is the idea of assets and liabilities. Assets are essentially described as whatever you own as valuable, and can be used for exchange in the community (ex.house).<br>Liability is the amount of value&#x2F;services you owe to another economic agent&#x2F;entity (ex.debt).</p><p>Now when we dig a bit deeper into those concepts, they can comprise of the same exact thing, but looked at from the perspective of different economic agents. If a bank has an asset it wants to give to a person (ex. money&#x2F;loan), that bank’s asset will be the person’s liability, and will still be the bank’s asset, but will be returned back to the bank piece-by-piece, in the form of a loan.</p><p>So we have one thing, such as the amount of money lent by the bank to a person, as being an asset from one angle (i.e. bank’s perspective), and a liability at the same time from the angle of the person taking the money (i.e. borrower). </p><h3 id="Now-what-usefulness-does-this-illustration-of-a-cycle-serve"><a href="#Now-what-usefulness-does-this-illustration-of-a-cycle-serve" class="headerlink" title="Now, what usefulness does this illustration of a cycle serve ?"></a>Now, what usefulness does this illustration of a cycle serve ?</h3><p>This idea of a cycle might have sounded trivial to mention, but my idea here is really a reminder, rather than a completely new insight, if you like.</p><p>And the reminder is really the fact that, I think establishing this way of thinking towards Economics provides a basis, and aids in making sense of economic phenomena with regards to its relation to other things, rather than trying to understand them in relative “seclusion”, let’s say. </p><p>As the economy is a complex system, to understand its parts, we have to be cognizant of the interconnectedness and interchangeability of different parts within that system&#x2F;cycle, and look beyond the specific part being investigated, and then come back and understand it in the grand scheme of things, if that makes sense. </p><p>So in the previous examples we saw that two things can be explained in different forms and terminology (for good reasons, obviously), but when we looked at them from another angle we understood that they are really inextricably the same thing, in some deep way.</p><p>So applying that analysis when we study things like money and supply &amp; demand is really key to try understand them in a deeper way.</p><p>And one more small tangential point I would like to mention is that this, in some sense, distinguishes Economics, from other disciplines. Because we hear conventional wisdoms like “focusing on one thing at a time is optimal for understanding”, but in Economics focusing on one thing is, in reality, focusing on a whole bunch of other things, implicitly.</p><h3 id="What-is-Money"><a href="#What-is-Money" class="headerlink" title="What is Money?"></a>What is Money?</h3><p>As surprising as this seems, but this question of “what is money ?” has been one of the most questions that has led me to other deeper branching questions in all sorts of domains, it’s just unbelievably interesting, to say the least. And hopefully this becomes obvious as we progress in thinking about it.</p><p>It’s good to start off by saying that money from a fundamental level is just a “technology”, that unifies otherwise dispersed possible processes. Just like the information in a computer can possibly exist “prior” to the computer, per se (in paper for example), the same can be applied to processes that money solves. However, the computer happens to bring the information in one place, and propagates it much faster and easier, and all sorts of interesting things emerge from that point.</p><p>The reason why I mention this is because money is sometimes identified with survival, reflexively, and although that’s true in modern society, but what I am trying to bring in consciousness here is that the essence of the idea of money is that it’s really a revolutionary technology that’s a relative necessity, rather than an absolute one. Another reason why I mention this is because it’ll kind of be important somehow in the upcoming understanding we’ll present, as we’ll try to build money as a concept from the ground up.</p></p><br>So In order for us to understand the concept more, it’s good to illustrate a money-less economy first, and then move to the principles of money and what it actually solves as a “technology” and what void it fills in a “money-less” economy. </p><h3 id="First-layer"><a href="#First-layer" class="headerlink" title="First layer:"></a>First layer:</h3><p>if we imagine an economy without money, everything would cost so much more time to attain, for example. Because you would have to <b>single-handedly</b> produce something (other than unified money), that people want first, in order to get something that other people produce.</p></p><p>So if you need some socks from a person who has the knowledge to make socks and you don’t, for example, you would have to provide something that the socks maker specifically needs, such as shoes, to exchange socks for shoes, for instance.</p></p><p>But that exchange approach will lead to the possible problem of the socks maker not needing your specific product or any service you provide, and then you can’t get the socks you need, for instance.</p></p><p>One question that might arise is:  Why do you need to give the socks maker something (shoe), rather than just nothing ?:<br><br>Well, You can think of the exchange as a “convincing mechanism” for the socks maker not to consume it himself or for his close ones. You need something to provide to start the convincing journey, and exchange is at the heart of this persuasion.</p></p><h3 id="How-money-fills-the-first-layer"><a href="#How-money-fills-the-first-layer" class="headerlink" title="How money fills the first layer:"></a>How money fills the first layer:</h3><p>Now money comes along in this context and says: “Both of you, shoe maker and socks maker, you don’t need to mutually need each others’ products for exchange, if the shoe makers wants socks, and the socks maker doesn’t want his shoes, just use me as an exchange mechanism. You, shoe maker, will get your socks,  and you, socks maker, can buy anything else you need from others in the economy, because I am accepted by everyone&#x2F;every service you can think of.”</p></p><p>So money serves not only as a medium of exchange, but a universal medium of exchange for traders.</p></p><h3 id="Second-layer"><a href="#Second-layer" class="headerlink" title="Second layer:"></a>Second layer:</h3><p>Now the second layer to deal with in our money-less economy is: to see how many socks are equivalent to a pair of shoes, and vice versa. So I have to negotiate the exchange of almost infinite services provided by different humans, without a unifying principle&#x2F;measurement governing the exchange.</p></p><p>So I would have to declare&#x2F;negotiate the exchanging measurement for almost every individual service&#x2F;exchange differently. So going back to the initial example, I would have to evaluate how many pairs of socks are worth the exchange of one pair of shoes. And then I would have to do the exact same process if I want to trade shoes for some butter, for example, and a difficulty of evaluating whether 7 grams, 8 grams, etc. of butter is worth a pair of shoes arises, and the process would start to become more hectic when we visualise different services within a whole economy.</p></p><p>If we put it in the context of a modern economy, and imagine Starbucks as an example of a money-less exchanger (although it’s almost impossible for Starbucks to exist without money), then Starbucks would have to negotiate with every customer how much of the specific products the customers is bringing to the table, is equivalent to a cup of coffee. One person would bring some wood, or another person might bring copper, for example, and the problem grows from there. Whether they need it or not is also another layer of the complexity of the situation, as aforementioned.</p></p><h3 id="How-money-fills-the-second-layer"><a href="#How-money-fills-the-second-layer" class="headerlink" title="How money fills the second layer:"></a>How money fills the second layer:</h3><p>So a monetary system would come in in this context, as a unifier of measurement. You only have one thing you need to measure the service&#x2F;good you’re providing against, which is money in this case. And this becomes more and more pertinent when we focus and try to contrast this with the aforementioned  money-less economy.</p></p><p>The abstract representation of that measurement of money is something we call a price. </p></p><p>The pricing system of money which is an integral part to call something money, solves an extremely difficult problem, which is to equate the service provided, in relationship to everything else in the economy.</p></p><p>Now you might be thinking, how do we even begin to set norms and prices when we take something as money ? assuming we had a money-less economy, and then we decided to shift, how do we set the “first price”, let’s say ?</p></p><p>The short answer is it’s arbitrary. We can’t really prove that our pricing system is a perfect tool that evaluates every single service in absolute justice. But the market and all complexities around the economy will make this process less and less arbitrary and more rigorous with further examination, let’s say.</p> </p><p>This point also comes back to the idea of money being a “technology”, because we can always come back and make reforms on its structure and how it’s propagated through space and time.</p></p><h3 id="Attributes-that-money-needs"><a href="#Attributes-that-money-needs" class="headerlink" title="Attributes that money needs:"></a>Attributes that money needs:</h3><p>So if we try to reconstruct our examples in a clearer way and state what money is explicitly, or what it possess, to be specific, we see that it has to bare three necessary components to be called “money”:  a universal unit of exchange ( I mean universal in a relative way, not an absolute one), a unit of measurement (as explicated), and a store of value. </p></p><p>Now it’s worth stressing that different forms of money optimize for those three things in different ways. Some forms of money compromise on one and make sure the other two are at their best utility. </p></p><p>So for example, a common form of money inside jails are tobacco cigarettes. Now tobacco cigarettes are not an optimal store of value , because tobacco companies can flood the market of tobacco in one day, and the cigarettes value will depreciate as the supply is increased. But it’s relatively a convenient medium of exchange, and can be easily measured, let’s say.</p></p><p>Another real-life example is paper money (or electronic forms of it), or government bank money used today in countries. It’s a great medium of exchange (easily divisible, and distributable across space), can be measured conveniently, however, it’s not the best store of value across time, because a government can essentially create unlimited amounts of money, and money could lose its value in the blink of an eye (extreme examples include Venezuela &amp; Zimbabwe).</p></p><p>So how does money lose its store of value ?<br><br>when money is created in an excessive manner, the prices in an economy will increase, because people have more printed money to buy things. </p></p><p>When people have more printed money, the prices in an economy rises as a result of increased money&#x2F;purchases, rather than a rise in price because of increased objective employment need, production, etc. (which should be the default of a price increase), and the cycle of price increase continues without any changes in objective production line&#x2F; additional employment, and it starts to lose value because its not representing the real dynamics of production in an economy, which should be its utility as a store of value.</p></p><p><b>(in case this representation doesn’t make sense to you, just try to add a time aspect to these things, because they usually take a long time to happen in the sequence presented).</b> </p><h3 id="Reconstructing-the-pieces"><a href="#Reconstructing-the-pieces" class="headerlink" title="Reconstructing the pieces:"></a>Reconstructing the pieces:</h3><p>By this time, you might have felt a bit confused by the discrepancy of the first part (economics as a cycle), and the second part about money, but I think we can kind of apply the same reasoning to money, as well. If we apply our thinking to money, we really see that money is just a commodity that shifts from being a commodity&#x2F;good (one part of the cycle), for example gold in ancient times, to becoming a medium of exchange (another part of the cycle). If we see it that way, we can understand that the same laws that apply to all other goods in an economy, really applies to money itself, and we can , by extension, vividly see how our reasoning can apply.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Economics</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Science and The Relevance of Its Philosophy</title>
    <link href="/2023/01/21/philoscien23/"/>
    <url>/2023/01/21/philoscien23/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Science as a source of knowledge, and as a practical application of that knowledge, in general, has endowed us with all sorts of improvements in the qualities of life, and a better understanding of the world around us, whether it’s medications that oppose fatal ailments, the understanding of general relativity, or computers&#x2F;devices to share information and create sophisticated systems with.</p><p>Given all the positive practical and theoretical consequences of this endeavour, it’s pretty easy to misplace this enterprise, and over-indulge in its benefits, and ignore understanding its philosophies, limits and short-comings. </p><p>Although science has, in principle, a built-in capability and mechanism to fix practical problems, it itself causes (ex. fixing pollution that is caused by scientifically-based inventions), a meta-level understanding, which can be described as the philosophy of science, will aid in:</p><ol><li><p><b>From a theoretical point of view, </b>learning the reach of the conclusions of science across space (what it investigates and what it doesn’t, in the grand scheme of things), and across time (whether its claims are ever ultimate&#x2F;set in stone across time), which by extension, curates our knowledge to try to be “closer to truth” or holistic, if that makes sense.</p></li><li><p><b>From an engineering point of view, </b> it’ll help us understand the secondary&#x2F;high-order effects that arise as a result of systematic inventions and technologies, and whether there are certain measures we need to think about other than the game-theoretic advantages of those technologies.</p></li></ol><p>Now, when I say understanding limits and short-comings, I don’t mean it necessarily in a bad way, but I mean it in the sense that, just as we understand the potentials of something, we have to equally understand its limits, <b>to some degree.</b></p><p>Because an activity or belief of some sorts, is not understood if its limits are not somehow delineated. If a human has a narcissistic approach to the world, and they try to fly by jumping off a roof, we say this person had an energy&#x2F;potential that could have been harvested in a more nuanced way (trying to invent a parachute to fly with, for example), but because they didn’t understand the limits of their approach at the time, that led to a loss of potential (jumping off of the roof).</p><p>Now that we examined the “over-indulgence” claim and how we can look at things from a broader angle, let’s examine some practical claims from scientists that actually reflect this rhetoric of ignoring “the philosophy of science”, as we laid it out until this point. And then we can progress to put everything in context with some details.</p><h2 id="Quotes"><a href="#Quotes" class="headerlink" title="Quotes:"></a>Quotes:</h2><p>“Fundamental science may almost be at an end and might be completed within a generation.”</p><ul><li>Chemist, Peter Atkins 1981.</li></ul><p>“Physicists might soon bring to an end a certain kind of science.”</p><ul><li>Physicist, Steven Weinberg 1992.</li></ul><p>“Our Existence once presented the greatest mystery of life. It is a mystery no longer, because it is solved. Darwin and Wallace solved it. Though we shall continue to add footnotes to their solution.”</p><ul><li>Biologist, Richard Dawkins 1986.</li></ul><h2 id="Definitions-and-clarifications"><a href="#Definitions-and-clarifications" class="headerlink" title="Definitions and clarifications:"></a>Definitions and clarifications:</h2><p> -Inductive reasoning is: when a conclusion, is a generalization from the premises (although people disagree with restricting it to generalizations, I think it’s a good first-pass approximation of understanding it). Another way of describing it is: when a populations’ behavior (conclusion) is judged from a sample of that population (premise).<br>So the typical example is: I see black swans all around me, I conclude that all swans are black.</p><p>But those propositions can be blown apart by any future disconfirmation of the premise (The black swan problem).</p><p> -Deductive reasoning is: When the conclusion necessarily follows from the premises. Deductive reasoning conclusions are embedded in the premises (as opposed to inductive arguments, which require a “leap” if you like), and they can be also be described as tautological, meaning that everything that will be stated in the conclusion, is already in the premises in some way, and that’s why they’re necessarily true.</p><p>If you didn’t quite understand the description, let’s give two examples:</p><ol><li><p>All men are fallible. Thamir is a man, therefore Thamir is fallible.</p></li><li><p>Another example is: 2+2&#x3D;4, (it’s worth mentioning here that mathematics is deductive).</p></li></ol><h2 id="Principle-1-Science-is-“paradigmatic”-not-absolute"><a href="#Principle-1-Science-is-“paradigmatic”-not-absolute" class="headerlink" title="Principle 1: Science is “paradigmatic”, not absolute:"></a>Principle 1: Science is “paradigmatic”, not absolute:</h2><p>Thomas Kuhn, a philosopher of science, has described and portrayed science, in a way that added a lot not only to science in relationship to itself, but also in relationship to knowledge as a whole. What he saw in the scientific enterprise as a distinguishing factor, is that it undergoes what he called “paradigm shifts”. Before we address the “shifts” part of his ideas, we can describe paradigms, crudely and generally, as: A common ground where scientists relatively agree on how to do things, what tools can be relevant, and what problems are important in that context.</p><p>Examples of paradigms include, new molecular genetics conceptions, which in turn include certain principles like: </p><ul><li><p>Organisms’ Genes are made up of DNA, with the exception of a few viruses that have RNA based genes.</p></li><li><p>Genes produce Proteins, and also regulate other genes. </p></li><li><p>Nucleic acids (DNA &amp; RNA) sequences specify the structure of Proteins.</p></li></ul><p>To get back to the “shifts” part, Kuhn described the flow of scientific disciplines  as an ever-changing endeavour that operates within a common paradigm (as we described it), and after some time, the paradigm “shifts” to a relatively new one, if it bumps into enough “irreconcilable” problems, and a more satisfying alternative is set forward. </p><p>Kuhn described the scientific enterprise as dealing with “puzzles” and “problems”. A puzzle is an issue that scientists face, with the assumption that it’ll be solved within the same common paradigm of the time, or in other words doing “normal science, let’s say. </p><p>Problems, on the other hand, is when a bunch of “puzzles” seem unsolvable given some time within the paradigm, and that is when the “shift” starts to appear within the paradigm. He stressed on the fact that science has, and should have a balance between reconciling puzzles, and knowing when the paradigm should be shifted or changed. </p><p>If scientists didn’t agree on any paradigm or any fundamentals to build on or to start with, Kuhn claimed that progress in any field would almost not be possible (he called this state “pre-paradigmatic” phase, where a lot of disciplines go through in their infancies, and he showed a bunch of examples like pre-newtonian physics).</p><p>Kuhn provided massive evidences for his claims, like the classical example of shifts from newtonian mechanics to Einsteinian relativity, and examples from other disciplines. Although some philosophers differed with Kuhn on how that change&#x2F;shift comes to be, what causes it, and whether multiple paradigms could exist at a specific time, his methodology and the evidences he provided were quite influential and insightful within the nature of science.</p><h2 id="Principle-2-Scientific-“models”-lead-to-workable-specific-theories-about-reality-not-absolute-truths-about-reality"><a href="#Principle-2-Scientific-“models”-lead-to-workable-specific-theories-about-reality-not-absolute-truths-about-reality" class="headerlink" title="Principle 2: Scientific “models” lead to workable specific theories about reality, not absolute truths about reality:"></a>Principle 2: Scientific “models” lead to workable specific theories about reality, not absolute truths about reality:</h2><p>A model’s function is to reduce the complexity to a set of variables that can be in turn investigated to understand a situation in a relatively particular way (particular relative to the whole of reality), and make predictions when applicable, but the model is always a reduction and is never a complete representation of what reality is, holistically (the words model and reality are being used loosely here). </p><p>It’s important to note here that, not every scientific conclusion&#x2F;description, in the broad sense of the term, is equal in its application of our principle. So for example, planetary shapes are things we can see with our eyes and they don’t really need “theorizing” initially, per se (let’s call it a description). </p><p>However, all things we see, in turn, require an explanation on how they became that way, on a more fundamental level, which will require theorizing. So to take our example one step further, we say that an explanation is needed on how planets shape themselves this way. Now some scientists mention that “gravity” is part of the reason why planets seem to shape themselves the way they do (let’s call this theory 1). Gravity, in turn, based on Newtonian conceptions used to be a pulling force, but as time progressed, einsteinian relativity came to replace it, and eventually described gravity as a pushing force and fundamentally changed our conception of gravity. </p><p>So to bring all of this into context with our principle, we see that the principle applies to scientific theories and scientific “descriptions” (as we defined it) differently. So the principle doesn’t probabilistically seem to touch our conception of planet earth’s shape that much, but it does probabilistically touch our theorization of how it came to be that way.</p><p>So from that perspective, we see that theories (as in the example we described), will always be “underdetermined” and under-representative of holistic reality, since theoretical interpretations try to “explain” things, and can be looked at 1) in different interpretations (at that time, or given some time), and 2) requires many assumptions that reduce the complexity and eliminate certain variables.</p><p>(Another example would be the Male-Female distinctive phenotypes (description), and explanatory theories of how they were shaped (theories of evolution, for example)).</p><p>The reason why I mention this is because the models can be easily conflated with reality in its holistic form, reflexively. And this reductionist point of view can be, in some contexts, detrimental to the understandings or approaches to the world. We see that practically happening, by people (ex. physicist Lawrence Krauss) alluding to the dispensability of some parts of logic or even deductive logic as an approach, as a result of some findings in quantum theory&#x2F;physics.</p><p>In this context, If we take parts of logic to be untrue, the consequences of that would be, the collapse of the evidence that was provided for the quantum theory that lead to the rejection of logic, for example. Evidence for anything would not even make sense in light of rejecting deduction, as its methodology construct the logic we think with in light of relating “observations” and theories.</p><p>An important point to mention here is that both sides of this example (induction and deduction), go hand-in hand in interpreting other phenomena, but understanding the principle and the things we presented is needed when things seem to ostensibly contradict each other, like in the case of Krauss’ interpretation of Quantum theory, and logic. And in this context, is when our principle and the things we said about it becomes really practical.</p><p>So now when we weigh in all the variables, and we understand that quantum theory is not necessarily in its complete form, since its inductive, while logic and deductive arguments are necessarily the case, we can hold that in our epistemic calculator when approaching the world, and come to say that maybe there is something we have yet to know about the details of quantum theory, rather than reject parts of deductive logic right away, for an inductive finding.</p><p>Just so we don’t lose track, I think we can think of the elaboration of this principle as an extension of the first one, since they overlap in some ways, but this one maybe addresses some smaller chunks of science rather than a whole paradigm, let’s say.</p><h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion:"></a>Conclusion:</h2><p>The point of these principles and definitions is to understand the philosophy of science, and have a birds-eye view on the scientific enterprise. To link this for the purposes we mentioned in the beginning, we came to understand that scientific theories are fundamentally inductive, and we also came to understand their philosophical probabilistic changing nature across time. On a day-day basis this might not be practically relevant, as science is a great way of understanding nature, that we should take “the word” from, so to speak, but given a holistic point of view, and when things seem to contradict each other, this representation serves us to flush out the confusion.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
      <category>Philosophy of Science</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>On the meaning of morality and life</title>
    <link href="/2022/12/18/moral/"/>
    <url>/2022/12/18/moral/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="The-purpose-of-Morality"><a href="#The-purpose-of-Morality" class="headerlink" title="The purpose of Morality:"></a>The purpose of Morality:</h2><p>You would think that we are just stating the trivially obvious here, but I think stating “the obvious” is always one of the best ways to understand a topic because “the obvious” is always, paradoxically enough, underestimated, and subconsciously brushed under the rug, so let’s start by exactly doing that. If we take a stroll down the purpose of morality, you would hear some people say that morality’s purpose is embedded in the idea in and of itself, but I think given today’s disputes&#x2F;differences on morality, it has gone too far to refer to the “intuitive”, and for that we need to substantiate each claim to begin to agree on the premises or the conclusions we make. It’s fair to start-off with what I call the consequential purpose of morality, which is: </p><p><b>1)</b> To counter-act&#x2F;correct the possible spectrum of some human tendencies. If we break this apart, we see here that we say “possible”, because there is an indefinite amount of different “tendencies”, different humans have. Some people will have a tendency to “kill” at different times, other people will have a tendency to sell drugs, and so, morality serves as a resistance to fill this “possible” hole of human tendencies and imperfections.</p><p><b>1.1)</b> But why should we have measures against the possible spectrum of some human “tendencies” ?<br>The answer to this is obvious with regards to very intuitive abhorrent practical acts like killing, for example. But it becomes less obvious with other measures that people differ on the “morality” of, like ingestion of Alcohol, for example. So to make sure we understand and establish “morality” against all domains we need to apply it to, let’s try to answer the question broadly enough. So, our ability to experience&#x2F;feel&#x2F;tend towards something, is finite (in other words, our “tendencies” are finite), but our ability to affect the world, ecology, society, other individuals, and ourselves, by extension, with those tendencies could be indefinite or disproportional relative to the tendency, and that unequal relationship should be accounted for when one is trying to convey life and act (i.e. morality). We can see that more clearly with regards to the analogy of prison systems. prisons, in principle, try to remind the possible criminal (who acted on a finite tendency of killing, for example) of the “indefinite” consequences the action has had, by a trial to inflict some of the effect the criminal did, back to the criminal, immediately when caught. Morality is a check against our possible “tendencies”, and actions according to them. </p><p>Now, the clarity between the two is extremely difficult to see in reality (not for intuitive things like stealing&#x2F;killing, for example), and usually the stances in morality between people diverge, because the effects that a human chooses to respond to are essentially predicated on what they see or prioritise as the meaning of life (to be expanded on later). If someone only cares about the state of their pleasure, for example, they will not be able to see or will ignore any effects outside the domain of that pleasure.</p><p>Before we get to the next part, it’s worth mentioning that we will examine below what’s a hopefully thoughtful deriving mechanism of “morality”, given the purpose we laid out (rather than an explicit extensive “morality”), by excluding some approaches, and then examining what was missing from them, and brainstorming our new hopefully understandable approach to identify what makes a deriving mechanism for morals.</p><h2 id="Issues-with-the-harm-principle-as-a-moral-stance"><a href="#Issues-with-the-harm-principle-as-a-moral-stance" class="headerlink" title="Issues with the harm principle as a moral stance:"></a>Issues with the harm principle as a moral stance:</h2><p>So some people would state that if you don’t harm anyone, you can do whatever you want. Some set that as a moral stance, which is really the tenet of social liberalism as we know it.<br>But I would say the stance is not a consistent or a sufficient one, for 3 reasons I can think of, given the “purpose” framework we established. But before we move on with that, those objections are not only being posed for some philosophical reasons, but because I also think they do have a lot of practical consequences, as well, as will be hopefully shown:</p><hr><b>(Whole numbers = Major Steps in our understanding).</b><p><b>(Decimals &#x3D; Details to be clarified with regards to certain Major steps).</b><hr></p><p><b>1)</b> When we say harm, it’s important to note what do we actually mean. Again, the concept of harm is very clear when it comes to intuitive concepts like killing, for example, however, the concept’s objectivity starts to dissolve when we look at differences between humans’ conception of harm. Examples include people’s differences on raising kids, some people would see that some measures are “harmful” clear-cut, other people wouldn’t see the same measures as harmful to the kids. To add to that, even if we say we know what the concept means and it’s really clear, it seems to me like “harm” implies a very direct type of effect, rather than one that includes all type of secondary&#x2F;tertiary&#x2F;etc. effects, which is insufficient as a descriptive model for “morality”, in my opinion.</p><p><b>2)</b> Another objection to put forward is that when we say “you can do anything, as long as you don’t harm anyone”, are we talking about reducing&#x2F;not enacting in net-harm (the aggregate), or really reducing&#x2F;not enacting in any type of individual harm that can be conceived ? Because if we go with the net-harm option (and add to that the vagueness of the concept we presented in 1), then really, we can say that it’s justified to “harm”, in order to produce less net-harm in the future, which leads to a contradiction, because how can one declare a moral stance, and go against it for a certain period of time?</p><p>A good real example of this would be prison systems: Governments “harm” criminals, to reduce less net-harm in society, and this example also tells us that the harm principle is not really descriptive even towards some basic legislative endeavours.</p><p>Now, If we take the second option and say any type of individual harm shouldn’t be enacted in, and the net-harm principle is not more important, then we run into releasing&#x2F;not imprisoning prisoners&#x2F;criminals in the prison system issue we presented, which also will end up with more individual “harm” in society, and that will also lead to a contradiction within that framework by the action of producing more “harm” (One can apply these examples in relationship to the self, it’s not necessarily societal).</p><p><b>3)</b> Harm, solely, as a moral stance, implies no real responsibility of the rational individual towards the world. An example of that would be, if I was walking down the street and I saw someone being beaten up for some material good (assuming there is no weapons  included), there is no “harm” in me just passing by without breaking up the fight, and that example (which maybe isn’t a good one), and others like it, take away from a lot of the responsibilities we should have towards the world. If the moral stance is really a passive principle that doesn’t push us for a responsibility towards our surroundings (which is an extension of us, in some sense), is it a “moral stance”, or is it just tendencies disguised in a new costume ? </p><p><b>3.1)</b> It would be a good addition if we contrast economic life to our example in (3). If we look closely into the economic life and our dynamics with money, making money actually makes us “defend” the man being beaten up, in the metaphorical sense of the term. Because if we look at the dynamics, we see that to get money (which is our self-interest, in some way), we have to provide something&#x2F;a service and a responsibility to the community by way of labor, or in other words, defend the guy being beaten up (i.e. have a sense of responsibility). (Of course, the economic system is not perfect to this purpose, some people steal, but in general, that is what usually happens). So in the economic world, we know very well that we are just too connected to detach one’s responsibility from society, ecology, etc., and that interconnectedness is not exclusive to the economic realm, but to every domain of life, we just have to look closely enough.</p><p><b>3.2)</b> As an extension of point 3.1, one would ask why should one (i.e. the individual) have a responsibility outside the domain of one’s experience? Why should one “break up the fight” or “prevent it in the future” with different measures?<br>We already understand the answer very well (as illicited in 3.1), from an economic perspective, by virtue of the existence of exchange or money in societies.</p><p>But to answer the question more broadly, One answer that could be thought about, is that responsibility outside the domain of the experience of the self, should be there because: the “individual” is fundamentally a misnomer, <b>from an effect perspective.</b> That is because, we are self-conscious enough to recognize that the fruits and effects of our actions go beyond the “individual”, so it can’t be adequate, encompassing, and&#x2F;or optimal to say that the “individual” ought to only deal with the direct effects to him&#x2F;her and others around only, when there is a <b>possible</b> disproportionality between the so called possible action of the “individual”, and the effects their actions have. And that’s why the “restriction of responsibility to the individual” approach is not wholly sufficient.</p><p>As Physicist David Bohm once wisely Said: “Everything is influenced by everything else.” </p><h2 id="Responsibility"><a href="#Responsibility" class="headerlink" title="Responsibility:"></a>Responsibility:</h2><p>When I say responsibility, I mean responsibility that reaches outside the self, in the sense that one abstains from an act <b>not</b> because one cannot fundamentally do it, but rather because the individual wouldn’t rather cause the consequences for things not only directed to the self and its domain (i.e. harm), but also outside the self and its domain (secondary&#x2F;tertiary&#x2F;etc. effects), and that is because as we said, everything is all a mesh of effects that interchangeably affect each other, and a “culture” of consciousness of this approach will by necessity optimize for the individual and the whole unit. And to stress on one point, effects on the individual themselves and their experiential domain is obviously part of the model, but what we are saying is that the individual and their direct interactions being the most priority in every situation in doing an action, will obviously not be sufficient in every context. </p><p>On a small addition, I think taking this responsibility will change the attitude of from: “They caused the issue, They should fix it”, to: “Hmm, maybe this problem is being contributed to by me acting in a certain blind way, let me try to think of my consequential actions, and aid in fixing the situation.” And a good example of that would be societal issues we have on scale, it seems like some issues exist, but nobody seems to be doing the thing that causes the issue (when obviously there are), for example, and I think that shows that we should account for the blind spots, and not act as “victims”, because sometimes part of our action was the perpetrator in some way, so we need to just constantly check against that, and “fix it ourselves”.</p><h2 id="The-meaning-of-life-morality"><a href="#The-meaning-of-life-morality" class="headerlink" title="The meaning of life &amp; morality?"></a>The meaning of life &amp; morality?</h2><p>Now that we are back to the relation of the meaning of life, I think the trajectory&#x2F;priority should go something like the flow illustrated below, otherwise, unknown meaning of life would lead to optimization for forces&#x2F;morality that cancel each other out, in some way (i.e. cognitive dissonance):</p><p>Meaning of life → Morality (practicality of that meaning&#x2F;meanings actualising, in some way)→ Tendencies.</p><p>To understand the model more, transgressing the “morality”, or an “immoral” act, would be jumping and prioritising a tendency that contradicts the meaning&#x2F;morality, for a certain period of time (this links back to the purpose of morality we mentioned).</p><h2 id="Wait-but-what-is-“meaning”-exactly"><a href="#Wait-but-what-is-“meaning”-exactly" class="headerlink" title="Wait, but what is “meaning” exactly?"></a>Wait, but what is “meaning” exactly?</h2><p><i style=font-weight:lighter;>(I hope this doesn’t make the concept more confusing (as it’s very intuitive), so feel free to skip through if you think this will confuse matters more.)</i> To be as clear as possible, meaning in our context is: the manifestation of causes and effects, that distinguishes one state from another. The meaning of a word is the manifestation of what it could&#x2F;would do (its causes &amp; effects, approximately not always entirely) that distinguishes the word from other words, when the analysis is properly placed. So meaning is almost the abstract blueprint, and morality is a practical achievement, in some way, of that purpose. Any conscious “meaning” requires counteracting some possible “tendency”, and that’s why we mentioned the purpose of morality as we mentioned it in the beginning.</p><h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion:"></a>Conclusion:</h2><p>So we see that the better we optimize for the economy, as an example, the better off every individual will be, by way of creating jobs or anything of that sort. But if we contrast this example, to lack of division of labor, and every single individual optimizes for something without reference to the economy or the whole, we say that this will forgo benefits for all entities and things within that unit.</p><p>That doesn’t just show us the importance in that specific economic domain, but it reminds us how the different parts of a system, are more or less, really part of the same dynamic of effects. </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Foundations and Philosophy of truth</title>
    <link href="/2022/11/15/truth/"/>
    <url>/2022/11/15/truth/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think It’s worth starting off with saying that it’s not at all obvious what the nature of this thing called “truth” is because <span id="more"></span> I think it requires, in turn, an understanding of a good amount of assumptions. But let’s try to lay it out and see what it means from an ‘Epistime’ &amp; ‘Techne’ perspective (Epistime &#x3D; knowledge or philosophical inquiry &#x2F; Techne &#x3D; practical applications of that Knowledge). I think it’s also worth mentioning that this is a humble trial to define and outline what truth is and what it does. I think of it almost like a first step to fundamentally understand where the idea of truth is rooted in our conception of the world, from first principles, and to understand it in a rational way, and also, from a philosophical perspective, to rationally move us past Nihilism, postmodernist solutions, or destructive skepticism (We’ll also make the case in an indirect sense, that destructive skepticism indeed exists).</p><h2 id="On-the-existence-of-Truth-The-why"><a href="#On-the-existence-of-Truth-The-why" class="headerlink" title="On the existence of Truth &#x2F; The why:"></a>On the existence of Truth &#x2F; The why:</h2><p>So in order for us to set the first step with a topic, we need to first justify that it actually exists first, because it’s not obvious, apriori, what assumptions are indispensable to start with even, but this one (existence of something) seems like a necessary one to continue with the topic. And It seems to me like thoughtfulness of assumptions should come before actually presenting theories of Truth, or taking any philosophical stances on the subject, per se. </p><p>Without delving into the rigorous actual definitions of truth first,  let’s first agree, that “Truth” must exist to start with the <b>human</b> experience itself, whether implicitly or explicitly, because ‘truth’ in some fundamental sense, is a function of the recognition of our ignorance relative to “reality”. If you believe in the two words mentioned in the last sentence, then we probably made it to the first step i.e. existence of “Truth”. Because If we think about it, what we are saying is <b>not</b> that truth&#x3D;ignorance, but rather, that the concept of “truth” arises when one accounts for their ignorance of the world, because a regulative process (i.e. “truth”, which will be detailed below) arises to counteract or “un-ignorize”, as soon as one realises ignorance (to be discussed more). And this exact “ignorance”, in turn, arises as a result of humans being a second-order reasoning beings (or reflecting on the processes of their own consciousness). So “truth” (its exact meaning to be discussed) must exist if we know that our ignorance is indefinite, whether from a macro (humanity level) or micro (individual level) perspective. One might think that this is circular because you can’t know you’re ignorant unless you presuppose a truth first, but I don’t think it is circular when we take it in isolation, primarily. Meaning that the first time we realised this process and recognition of ignorance exists period, is not when truth as we know it becomes clear (let’s call it semi-truth at this stage), but rather when we realise our ignorance is <b>“indefinite”</b> and we apply “Semi-truth” abstractly&#x2F;universally enough, is when what we said about “truth” becomes relevant.<br></p><p>In addition to what we said about the existence and the condition of truth above, you might think that we should apply a second condition, which is to believe that we can “un-ignorize” ourselves in the first place, in order to believe in the existence of truth, because it wouldn’t make sense as a process if that’s not the case, it would just be a descriptive state of something rather than a thing we “pursue” (even in the case of everyday scenarios, we usually think of it as a process, rather than a description). But I would say that this claim is implicit in the word “ignorance”, by definition, because what it means is: What is known relative <b>to what could be known</b>, and since this is the case, one need not to mention this condition of ignorance being a “changeable state” explicitly, since it’s already implied in its definition. So the claim that we just can’t know anything that is true (to be defined), is almost untenable, by definition, if one agrees with the points&#x2F;conditions we laid out until this point.</p><p>Now what we said is a second-order concept, meaning it’s as a result of  human consciousness reflection on  itself. I am re-mentioning this because it gives us some kind of provability that the existence of truth is in fact, somehow and in one way, predicated and realised upon the idea of our ignorance, because if we contrast our case with first-order reasoning beings (like most animals as far as we know, for example), we see that they can only react to that which they directly experience or “know” (if we project human terminology), and not that which they don’t “know” or are ignorant about, and that doesn’t seem to be a sufficient condition for the existence of truth (ignorance&#x2F;knowing are a bit of a misnomers here in the case of animals, since, as far as we know, they’re incapable of “knowing”, in the first place, but it’s being used loosely here). So  “truth” is ,in one way, declaring consensus on the ignorance of human kind at different levels of analysis (i.e micro&#x2F;macro). </p><p>Note that there are two aspects of what we said in the previous paragraphs; knowledge and truth. Now in some sense they are interchangeable. Because truth is embedded within the definition of knowledge, And knowledge is embedded within the definition of truth. But in a lot of other ways they are different. To clarify and extend on the first “ignorance” point we laid out, let’s set some definitions on the table so we understand what we’re talking about here: Knowledge is true, justified belief (although an extremely debated definition, let’s go with this one for now). We’ll leave the definition of truth aside for now, and try to define it as we’re building our points next.<br>Now, Let’s lay out this weird dynamic of these two concepts in a step-wise approach and see how it relates to the aforementioned idea of “ignorance”, while keeping the previously mentioned definition of knowledge in mind when going through the steps:</p><p><b>(Whole numbers &#x3D; Major Steps in our understanding).</b></p><p><b>(Decimals &#x3D; Small details to be clarified with regards to certain steps).</b></p><ol><li>Humans have ways to deduce things about the world (5 senses, and&#x2F;or reasoning). The “belief” part of  Knowledge, let’s say, emerges here.</li></ol><p style=font-weight:lighter>1.1) Whether you believe in an <a href=" https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idealism ">idealist</a> approach to the world or a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philosophical_realism">realist</a> approach, Step 1 still holds up.<ol start="2"><li><p>Humans can reflect on the processes of their brains, propositions, and beliefs, and how they understand the world (Second-order, third-order reasoning, etc.).</p></li><li><p>Humans realise&#x2F;realised and recognize their place and indefinite ignorance with regards to the “real world” they experience (if you’re a realist), or their common experience (if you’re an idealist). You can think of part of truth emerging here in some sense. </p></li><li><p>Now that we acknowledge our ignorance about the world, next step would be to outline how we can become less “ignorant” about the world, which is almost like another part of truth.</p></li></ol><p style=font-weight:lighter>4.1)) This will be addressed in the “how” part below.    <p>It’s seems to me, at least in my conceptualisation, thinking about it this way, primarily, flushes out the difficulty to understand the concept. </p><p>Now don’t get me wrong at this stage, we only explicated <b>why truth should exist</b> rather than what it is. We only touched some elements of what it is implicitly, which we will be extending more upon next.</p><h2 id="What-is-truth-The-what"><a href="#What-is-truth-The-what" class="headerlink" title="What is truth ?&#x2F; The what:"></a>What is truth ?&#x2F; The what:</h2><p>The two ways we can approach this is to mention mainstream definition of truth which is something like: Truth is the correspondence of beliefs to facts. But this definition just seems to me like a definition for the pros, and not for difficult-to-grasp-anything people like me. So the other way would be to mention my original-idea mode definition which goes something like this (it might seem complex, but I’ll break it apart piece by piece):<br>Truth is the transcendent regulatory abstract concept on the epistemology of a second-order (or third-order, etc) conscious being. Let’s break this apart: </p><ol><li><p>The transcendent part here just means that we can’t really know something without it being questioned in the name of this thing called “truth”, it also stays as a checking mechanism concept above any form of “knowledge” we are trying to deduce, and that’s why it’s <b>transcendent</b> relative to the knowledge&#x2F;epistemology, in that sense.  </p></li><li><p>It’s regulatory in the sense that it has limits, and anything that lies outside those limits is something we call “false” or “untrue”. We can incorporate here the mainstream definition we mentioned above, and say that the regulation is the:<br>The correspondence of beliefs&#x2F;propositions with facts (although controversial, but we’ll make the case for it as we go).</p></li></ol><p>It has limits in another sense which is the truth-bearing of statements, or beliefs, meaning that not any sentence we make will bear truth or falsehood, and an example of that would be a question because it’s not asserting anything about an issue at hand, so we say it’s laying beyond the relevance of truth.</p><ol start="3"><li><p>It’s abstract because we can’t realise truth as it is, until we grasp things we have present limitations in understanding, <b>universally</b> enough to understand it to be a part of our knowledge of the universe and experiences, let’s say. Otherwise we’d either deem as non-existent, or we’d constrain it to certain types of knowledge, and leave it out of others.</p></li><li><p>Also, when we say second-order or more, we mean that this consciousness or conscious being is able to ,in turn, reflect on its self or processes that’s seeking this “knowledge”, extensively. Truth is a meta-process, in that sense, which is a necessary element of its existence.</p></li></ol><h2 id="Facts-and-truth-relation"><a href="#Facts-and-truth-relation" class="headerlink" title="Facts and truth relation:"></a>Facts and truth relation:</h2><p>Now you might ask, where does “reality” and “facts” fit into this definition? In addition to what we said in point 2 above with regards to this question, I think we can extend upon it a bit to understand it more, so here is another way I look at it with an analogy: If we take the analogy of an orange-colored room, full of oranges and tangerines, then let’s imagine we are looking for the most sour orange in that room. Now let’s link this to our concepts; truth would be analogous to us recognizing that we may or may not find the most sour one (let’s imagine this is the case because of the limitations of our taste buds), at the same time, with this limitation in place, we can initiate methodologies and “regulations” to “un-ignorize”, such as recognizing the tangerines by shape and ruling them out as the most sour ones, or by the lightness of the color of the orange. A Fact would be relevant in this analogy as the case that we “know” there is, objectively, the most sour one, which is a necessary part of undergoing the previously mentioned processes. The analogy might be a bit of a fallacious one, but without juxtaposing the analogy too much with the details of our topic, we see in this analogy a link between a fact and the truth in the sense that the fact is probably a raw description, while the truth is a process in some sense, and they’re both aiming at the same thing and interchangeable in a lot of ways (as it’s the case in everyday life).</p><h2 id="Deflationary-theory"><a href="#Deflationary-theory" class="headerlink" title="Deflationary theory:"></a>Deflationary theory:</h2><p>This is somehow a change of flow from the things we have been laying out in the previous paragraphs, or will lay out after, but this part seems to me like a reasonable supplement and a useful tangent to try to understand the concepts discussed more, and to give us some perspective from a somehow pragmatic sense. Deflationary theorists of Truth claim that truth is redundant to think about as a “real” concept because it’s essentially identical to the things we believe to be the case, in other words, it’s not very important to account for this abstract notion in our reasoning because it’s just another way of saying something is a certain way, And an example of this would be comparing: “It’s true that the sky is blue” vs “The sky is blue”. But I think it’s a mistake to dismiss the concept as a whole because, as we laid out previously in an implicit sense, when we set truth in a deflationary fashion, our ignorance about the world starts to become less visible in some sense. But when we have this bird’s eye view on our knowledge, we become “humbled” relative to our place and knowledge of the world.<br>It is not obvious to me that a deflationary theory approach would work with a self-reflective flawed system of knowledge, like human beings knowledge.</p><h2 id="Dynamics-The-how"><a href="#Dynamics-The-how" class="headerlink" title="Dynamics &#x2F; The how:"></a>Dynamics &#x2F; The how:</h2><p>Now one question would be: what do we use to check our beliefs against this <B>regulative process of beliefs that is fundamentally attached to reality (i.e. truth)?</B></p><p>So first, When we think about our thoughts we start off with a bundle of wallowing dispersed “thoughts” that are waiting to be coordinated using language, so first coordinative process, language. Let’s call it truth 1. Then we add a coordinated process to language itself and its extensions and meanings, logic (Both logic and language are temporally attached, so it’s not clear which one ”comes first”). Let’s call it truth 2. And from that point on, there are  different extensions of logic and language, when it’s properly placed, such as science, philosophy or Theological religious revelations, in the case of religion. So this shows us how the regulative process of truth uses these tools in service of its purpose (to put it in a somehow abstract form).</p><h2 id="Why-Logic"><a href="#Why-Logic" class="headerlink" title="Why Logic ?"></a>Why Logic ?</h2><p>One might ask, Why logic as a foundation and not something else to get to the “truth” ?<br>Well, one answer is that: 1) logic is the only way where anything is actually distinguishable from anything else in a meaningful sense, as soon as it’s abandoned (which is not possible in any meaningful sense), everything literally becomes everything (whatever that means, I hope it at least just barely makes sense). If we take a thought experiment and say we’ll abandon logic, that statement itself is logical because one assumed that there is something called “logic”, and whatever other thing you want to abandon “logic” for, which is itself a logical distinction. 2) It’s a self-capitulating question, since one is actually using logic to produce the question itself. 3) The functioning of intelligence and consciousness must have distinctions and patterns, since it’s computationally finite, and this can’t be achieved except with logic. I am aware that this might be circular, since it’s referring to logic using logic, but this is actually my point in some sense (i.e. it can’t be not used, in any meaningful sense).</p><h2 id="Truth-is-objective"><a href="#Truth-is-objective" class="headerlink" title="Truth is objective:"></a>Truth is objective:</h2><p>Truth is objective in the sense that it varies independently of anyone’s perception of it. It’s accurate that everyone has different “access” to truth based on how their different beliefs integrate with each other, however, it doesn’t necessarily follow that we dismiss an objective regulation, because one of its basis is for our beliefs to be actually “challenged”, and that simply can’t be done when it’s described as subjective or intersubjective. In fact, a contradiction would arise if we acquiesce to truth being subjective, because as soon as we do that, the concept of truth collapses into a belief, which is the essential element truth is in service of keeping in check. So this is almost like a reductio ad absurdum, or proof by showing the opposite (subjectivity of truth) to be contradictory.</p><h2 id="Practical-side-of-it"><a href="#Practical-side-of-it" class="headerlink" title="Practical side of it:"></a>Practical side of it:</h2><p>What could be some practical sides of this thing we call truth? What consequences does it hold in a practical sense?<br>Truth is, in some sense, the essence of all “errors” we confess to ourselves and others from a practical perspective, because errors necessitate the existence of objective truth, since they require an “outsider’s” perception. Truth is also the ultimate common ground for any language and communication. a dialectic is just utterly not possible without truth, because if we obliterate the concept as we illustrated it today with a complete understanding of the consequences, All aspects of human endeavours, from trying to understand emotions to trying to understand the stars is just not possible without somehow re-presupposing truth as we explicated it today. <hr><br><img src="/img/Tt.jpeg"></p><hr><p><b>This is a brief visual representation about the things discussed.<br>As soon as one realises their “indefinite ignorance”, which is drawn as a circle in the illustration, a road like the one drawn, has to be the case, to make sense of the world and understand it.</b></p><h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion:"></a>Conclusion:</h2><p>We have laid out some thoughts about truth here and there, and I think it’s fair to mention that these paragraphs deviate from mainstream literature in the nature of the assessment, in the sense that I think the points of view I presented somehow address foundational assumptions of the topic rather than present theories or stances on truth. In conclusion, I think that truth, to put it in a somehow poetic form, is the guardian angel of collective intelligence. And we might not think of it like this, but it’s one pillar that keeps our consciousness and collective consciousness in check with regards to the world and how we approach it.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>The dynamics between “Theoretical” &amp; “experimental/practical” knowledge</title>
    <link href="/2022/10/12/dynam/"/>
    <url>/2022/10/12/dynam/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are all sorts of difficulties, at least in my conceptualization, in rigorously dividing the two “aspects” of knowledge we mentioned in the question, because these two aspects of knowledge might be more intertwined than we think, but for the sake of understanding the world just a little bit more, let’s give it a try and separate them for now. </p><h3>Definitions: </h3><p><b>Theory&#x2F;theoretical knowledge:</b> is the explanation of phenomena using human reason, abstract reasoning, and conjectures to understand the case&#x2F;situation at hand. It has to do with understanding things as a priority, rather than implementing them, per se.</p><p><b>Practical&#x2F;experimental knowledge:</b> “Real world” applications or innovations of the models we have built as conjectures in the theoretical knowledge part (the applicable ones). You can think of it as the implementation&#x2F;testing of theoretical knowledge. </p><h3>Looking at it from the Macro level: </h3><p>First, one thing to mention that can clarify things a bit is that: every practical&#x2F;experimental piece of knowledge has a theory “behind” it, or at least will have one in the future. However, the opposite is not necessarily true.<br>To put it another way, the probability of applying theoretical knowledge <b>directly</b> to the “real world”, or taking it further than mere “understanding”, is pretty lower (although not minuscule) than endeavours that actually have a focused direct practical side to them, as far as I understand them. Which is one important reason, I think, for why some people are not very enthusiastic to “engage” in theoretical knowledge at the first look, per se (ex. people not excited to take theoretical University courses).</p><p>Examples of this include the dynamics between mathematics and engineering. If you’re operating mainly within the realm of pure mathematics and excelling at that (not the applied types), you might probably do a lot of math, and not see it end up in the newest engineering models of a computer for quite some time, for example. But doing some legit engineering would necessitate grasping some mathematics, which proves the point we mentioned above more with regards to their interactions.<br>Now to go back to theoretical knowledge, the exciting part of it, and the thing we come to learn throughout the decades, is that we can never know if this piece of “theoretical” knowledge will be directly applied to the “real world” or not in the future, and one reason that comes to my mind to explain this is that: there are no configurational limits to what we can “build” in the outside world (although fundamental limits include laws of physics), so we can never know what valid theoretical knowledge will be directly applied in the future models of new inventions, even if that piece of knowledge seems solely about “understanding” rather than implementing, at the moment.</p><h3>Theoretical knowledge and novelty:</h3><p>It also seems to me like pure theoretical knowledge is directly proportional to novelty in some way. The more someone “understands” the thing more on a deep level that somehow transcends Practicality at the first instance, the more they’ll probably produce something completely new out of the issue in hand. Now, to bring this point back to reality, no discipline is purely practical or purely theoretical, they’re both overlapping in a lot of ways, but rather we can look at this arbitrary correlation and align it with an individual’s micro level novel achievements, rather than on a disciplinary&#x2F;macro level.</p><h3>Micro level:</h3><p>.…Speaking of the micro level, we may have discussed the macro disciplinary aspect of it up until this point, but let’s hold on to this for a second, and speak about it from the individual’s perspective rather than on a macro&#x2F;societal level. Theoretical knowledge teaches one how to think about the world, even if it doesn’t get applied directly in a disciplinary “real world” setting. You can think of it almost as a relative imaginative practice for brain power that will necessarily come to translate into solving real-world problems, <b>if we assume we looked closely enough into that theoretical knowledge.</b> I can’t help but to include the example of Philosophical endevours. It’s useful in our context here to think about the usefulness of philosophy because you can think of it as analogous to “theoretical” knowledge in some way. Now, in my opinion, I think philosophical endevours interestingly will teach one how to think systematically with regards to other endevours of life, even if the topic at hand is not <b>obviously</b> applicable to real-world scenarios. one just has to look closely enough into the act of “philosophizing”. And this seems to me equally applicable to the dynamics of theoretical and experimental knowledge.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>One conclusion we can come to after thinking about this question (and my random answers about it) from a macro and micro level is that: both practical and theoretical knowledge are equally important in the trip of life. Putting one over the other, ontologically, doesn’t seem like the optimal way to go, because both of them seem to construct our productive realities in some way, whether the individual is absorbing&#x2F;seeking or producing that knowledge.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Extras/Questions</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mesmerised With Labels</title>
    <link href="/2022/08/22/mesmerise/"/>
    <url>/2022/08/22/mesmerise/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="The-structure-of-identity"><a href="#The-structure-of-identity" class="headerlink" title="The structure of identity:"></a>The structure of identity:</h3><p>It’s important to first see from the outside what’s the structure of our identities as humans. Because we get so much input from the world (as a result of our consciousness), we need to distinguish what things we understand to be a part of our identity. We can consider the first layer of our identity as biology&#x2F;body (notice here we didn’t say sex, we said biology because it includes but is not restricted to sex). You can think of our biology as the prime mover in some sense. After that biology gives rise to brains, which is subject to process an innumerable amount of input with its structure. This brain or group of brains give rise to personality, feelings, and cultures, which brings us to the second part of identity which is the relatively abstract part.  We can see this distinction of first&#x2F;second parts of identity becoming clear because we strive to “find ourselves” in the abstract part (our ideas, feeling, etc.), but we don’t strive to find our biological sex, for example. This is not to dismiss its validity, but just to prioritise what things build a human being.  </p><h3 id="Gender-as-a-concept"><a href="#Gender-as-a-concept" class="headerlink" title="Gender as a concept:"></a>Gender as a concept:</h3><p>Having distinguished multiple parts of identity, let’s take a look at what gender looks like inside that identity. Gender is a lot of the times described as the characteristics that humans (male&#x2F;female) manifest. Some people would mention that those characteristics are socially constructed, other people say it’s biological differences, but it seems like it’s a difficult line to draw for the perception of a lot of people because the argument has gone way too political in some sense, and people vary in their definitions very much. I feel like for these reasons, it makes much more sense to actually reconstruct the concepts from the ground up so we can know where the exact points of divergence lie, rather than jump to the scientific literature explicitly, per se.</p><p>Let’s start off with the first part talking about a new angle to look at what gender really is, and then in part two, we’ll look into the concept from a more psychological perspective.</p><h3 id="1-New-way-of-thinking-about-gender"><a href="#1-New-way-of-thinking-about-gender" class="headerlink" title="1): New way of thinking about gender:"></a>1): New way of thinking about gender:</h3><p>The misinterpretation of those words “Masculine” and “feminine” is probably one of the most important factors that lead some people to experience gender confusion. “Masculine” and “feminine” descriptions (gender) of human behavior are statistical in nature, meaning they are not absolute descriptions of biological male&#x2F;female temperaments. What follows from this is that both biological males and females can show attributes and activities of either masculine&#x2F;feminine temperament (think of it as describing the activities not the humans). However, they were attributed to male&#x2F;female because it seems like on average the masculine attributes (and the extremes of it) are more common in biological males, and vise versa. That doesn’t say anything absolute about one’s identity, it means that a few scientist&#x2F;observants looked into the world, and saw the correlation between the masculine temperament (whatever that includes) and men - feminine temperament and women, which means that all other genders that claim to be emerging (non-binary, gender-fluid, trans) are redundant, because the descriptions we have are not at all absolute&#x2F;definitive. What by extension follows from this is that gender need not to be projected to any fundamental biological phenomena since it’s a statistical observation to describe the activities&#x2F;feelings we manifest. There is another aspect to this that some people would actually like to add, which is gender identity. Now, if we understand the concept of gender as presented above, then we can extract that it taps into an external phenomena, and what “gender identity” implies is an explanation of an internal human experience (internal&#x2F;external is just a distinction between things that can be seen, and things that go on inside the brain before that external thing happens). Now the idea of gender identity tries to extract an internal explanation out of an external one, and the problem that arises is that the external explanation is usually an oversimplified category of the act. If we look at what gender tells us, it describes feelings&#x2F;activities we manifest into the real world, which is somewhat a simplification of what goes internally in the human mind before manifesting that specific action. So what we are saying essentially is that the external categorization might not hold up as an accurate one with the internal phenomena (i.e. identity). If we take a classical example of dolls&#x2F;cars female&#x2F;male dichotomy, we see that if a boy likes to play with a doll, from the outside its explanation might be that this person, according to the averages of people, falls under feminine temperament with regards to this specific activity. When we come to the internal aspect of that, a number of possibilities (consciously or subconsciously) might actually be the case (and they might be completely detached from our outside categorization), like that child likes the color of that doll, or maybe that doll reminds him of his mom, or maybe he was in a “mood” (whatever that includes) to try something different. And what those explanations might end up doing is nudge the person to confine to this pseudo-explanation of their activities and identity. To conclude with this point, if somebody comes along and says: that boy is a girl trapped inside a boy’s body, they have made an inaccurate observation for two reasons: 1) The liking of that certain doll is present in both biological males and females, but on average females tend to show more interest for it (You can refer to the people-things distinction), which means no “trap” is present if we take a look from this angle. If you say “a girl is trapped in a boy’s body” or vice versa, for doing any activity, you’re essentially saying “Most girls play with dolls, therefore if you play with dolls you’re a woman” (you can extend this even if there are a multiple of other activities&#x2F;things, the argument still holds). 2) There is an attempt to project an external phenomena of playing with dolls (or interest in people broadly speaking), to explain&#x2F;categorize an internal phenomena (the person’s identity). Of course, the external is related somehow to the internal, but it’s not a sufficient description of it. We can see this distinction becoming clear because we see millions of people doing the same act (external), but for innumerable different reasons (internal).    Imagine if we categorize people on how fast they walk. So let’s say that when a group of experiments were done, biological males were found to be walking slower than females. Now imagine if after this experiment people start to relate this observation internally and project it to biological sex (i.e. a male saying I walk fast, therefore I “feel” like a female). Now that person might actually change their behavior with regards to other activities based on a one external correlation that says walking fast is predominantly a female act, which creates a loop inside his brain (to be discussed in more detail in (2)). So we can see clear in this example that walking fast&#x2F;slow is just a hypothetical correlation, it doesn’t mean there’s a causal relationship between it and identity. If we think about gender this way, This presented argument holds up whether you believe these statistical manifestations are socially, or biologically constructed, or both actually.  When we put it in a context of statistical analysis, The concept of gender becomes clear that it’s about individual activities and not human beings in the strict sense of the term. What gender identity does is it treats those aspects of gender as an absolute bundle to a person, and not the activity itself. Which might end up skewing one’s analysis of themselves.</p><h3 id="2-Psychological-consequences-of-progressive-Gender-theory"><a href="#2-Psychological-consequences-of-progressive-Gender-theory" class="headerlink" title="2):Psychological consequences of progressive Gender theory:"></a>2):Psychological consequences of progressive Gender theory:</h3><p>Let’s assume that the analysis in part 1, is just not accurate, is there another layer to it we can look at this from? Well, let’s see what another perspective of this looks like, which is a more psychological aspect, if you like.  One of the other problems I see evident with the progressive concept of gender today is that it stresses very much to overcategorize people in a definitive way. When we say overcategorize, we mean it in the sense that there’s an attempt to categorize complex experiences (ex. I like to play with boys) to reductionally-oriented models (new gender labels&#x2F;concepts) that are shallow with regards to the experiences and just don’t fit the complexity of the situation (in some sense, this is relatable to the external&#x2F;internal distinction mentioned above). And the “over” part is important here because what we mean by that is: Every experience will be crammed subconsciously inside that inaccurate model, and this distorted model that’s not fit for purpose becomes an eye you see experiences with in some fundamental sense. Think of it with regards to this example, if a biological female one day, after having a group of experiences, decided that she has “masculine gender”, (which is a redundant description if we understand the concept of gender as mentioned in part(1)). if we go on with that person’s conception, what happens in the mind is that a new abstract feedback loop will be created (subconsciously), and what that feedback loop will do is push that person to confine to this category in an absolute way, which ironically limits the person more so than it frees them. And speaking of psychological effects, language is a huge part of it, and inventing new words like “non-binary”, and treating it as a freeing concept from everything is in reality a much more restrictive category than anything because it’ll subconsciously push that person away from whatever thing they consider as “binary” (it’s also worth mentioning that the lack of proper definitions of these concepts pushes forward this loop). The issue with this feedback loop is that it’ll be difficult to add new information to that loop given new experiences. The political movement on those things also adds on to the lack of information not entering the calculations of that person, and one outcome that might end up happening is a projection of these ideas to identity in an absolute confident sense. You can extend this to say that we have limited amount of information about “categorizing” our experiences, which doesn’t seem to be an assumption in the gender identity narrative. At the end of the day, we see the world with the models we put forward to explain ourselves and the things around us in some fundamental sense. But when it comes to gender as we said in part (1), it’s an objective probabilistic observation that describes people’s reactions&#x2F; temperaments to the world, and not at all tries to put a whole internal human experience to an inappropriate frame&#x2F;category.</p><h3 id="Irrationality-bounded-rationality"><a href="#Irrationality-bounded-rationality" class="headerlink" title="Irrationality&#x2F;bounded rationality:"></a>Irrationality&#x2F;bounded rationality:</h3><p>In order to understand one side of the discussion, I think it’s important to talk a bit about rationality (which can be seen as a meta-identity analysis in some sense). We know that as humans, even though the capability to reason is within us (i.e. brains), we need to “cancel out” our irrationality in order to reason relatively clearly about the world. But a good question is: how does this irrationality even arise to begin with ? One answer is because the brain integrates data in such a huge way (consciously or subconsciously), the principles of making rational decisions actually become much more difficult with bigger neurological circuits, since the conscious brain (think of it as the part that makes the final decision) can’t keep up with all the data so it almost cherry picks some feelings, thoughts which allow for a “bad decision” to happen sometimes. It’s much more probable for someone to forget the tasks they want to do when they have a lot of them, and the brain is almost analogous to this, so keeping a hypothetical to-do list might make it easier for the person to actually remember what to do. The same applies with the constituents of identity, the more you get input from culture, society, feelings and activities the more likely your thoughts are to be distorted on what decision is actually optimal for identity.  Which means that every decision we need to make has to go through steps to cancel out noise in that decision. It’s almost like the bigger the neurological circuit, the more you’re losing track of why you made a decision, and rationality&#x2F;practicing and challenging our feelings and thoughts is the way to actually organize these structures of data and think of what’s actually optimal for us as humans.</p><h3 id="conclusion"><a href="#conclusion" class="headerlink" title="conclusion:"></a>conclusion:</h3><p>My main objective of the previous paragraphs is not to actually dismiss any problem people have, but rather shift some perspective to see this from another angle, because Problems and their existence are a lot of the times conceptual in nature. And by necessity, their solutions can be conceptual as well, so sometimes maybe a good way to look at things is to change and tweak the building “concepts” of some idea or belief, and see where that would take us with regards to our analysis of the world.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Human Nature</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Is Every Problem Solvable?</title>
    <link href="/2022/07/05/problemso/"/>
    <url>/2022/07/05/problemso/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This question keeps knocking at the door of reality in some sense, because in one way we perceive the world as a set of problems. It might seem like an obvious question, you have problems and solutions, </p><p>you untangle these two, and there you go you have the answer. But in order to get to the bottom of this question, we need to dig deeper to understand how these two concepts (problems&#x2F;solutions) relate to reality.<br>You would think of some problems as an objective measure in all aspects (since we try to solve a lot of them together as humans, whether in science, companies, projects, or personal endeavours), but if we strip problems out,<br>they include assumptions inside them,</p><p>and those assumptions in turn are predicated on perceptions of human beings mostly (you can kind of think of these perceptions&#x2F;assumptions as axioms,<br>if we are speaking mathematically).</p><p>Now, having cleared out what problems are in some sense, we can look at this question and answer it from two angles that touch each other in some sense. The first is: we as humans will, practically, keep “making up” problems because it’s a function of our perception, </p><p>and our perception changes with the environment and the things we create, and the cycle will run ad infinitum as long as we perceive the world in a continuously dynamic way, So from a practical perspective we say problems will run infinitely (in the loose sense of the term). So that’s from a practical perspective.<br><br>Another way we can approach the question is to try to answer the question in principle, essentially, without the details of practicality.<br>It might seem like it’s clear that the human mind is able to answer to any problem in principle, </p><p>but in my opinion, this is far from being conclusive (not wrong just early to make conclusions on). The issue with this approach is that it doesn’t account for the fact that solutions themselves generate problems by way of causality, and also solutions themselves might be looked at as problems given some time. This is because the spectrum of our perception is innumerable in the things it perceives,<br>and is subject to change given information, and by way of that fact, we can’t make a conclusive answer to this latter question.</p><p>In some sense, our question today is meaningless to start with because we don’t seem to understand what’s the line that separates problems from solutions. It might be clear in using tools like mathematics, but in the real world, the line is blurred in some sense.</p><p>But to conclude, one practical approach to life is to assume that every problem (meaning everything we perceive as a problem) at hand can be approached in one way that eventually will lead to a solution (whatever practical thing we mean by that word). It’s an assumption in science and every other human endeavour that is extremely useful to the way we approach the world.  </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Extras/Questions</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Detection of Life As We Don&#39;t Know It</title>
    <link href="/2022/05/26/deteclife/"/>
    <url>/2022/05/26/deteclife/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The possible positions on mysteries of life beyond earth has been crazy varied between people. And people seem to understand it and have a position on it in all sorts of different ways. Some people think of the movie like version of life outside earth, others think it’s non-existent, others have the possibility of any life form occurring extra-terrestrially, and others have really just not thought about it very much to build an opinion about the matter. But it’s worth taking a route down some nuances on this topic, and building a relatively systematic way of seeing it. </p><h3 id="Defining-life"><a href="#Defining-life" class="headerlink" title="Defining life:"></a>Defining life:</h3><p>It’s not an exaggeration to say that a consensus on defining life (even between the scientific community) has never been achievable until this day, and there are a bunch of definitions floating around when it comes to “life”.</p><p>So while we are at it, let’s take the challenge of first defining life:<br>Well, let’s say that life is the ability of a system to be actively nutritious in the sense that they extract their source of survival from things whether inside and&#x2F;or outside of them (At least, Life on earth until now, to be specific). And the actively nutritious part here is very important I think, because stars can get quite “nutritious” on other planets and other celestial bodies, but the “actively” part here is the ability to actually adapt in certain relatively counter-nutritious contexts, but in the case of the star, that’s the job of the laws of physics and not the star’s adaptability itself to provide “nutrition” in this definition. A monkey would relatively defy gravity to climb a tree and get some food, a bacterium would invade other organisms </p><p>with conditions that might get them killed, and plants require water to initiate photosynthesis. It’s worth noting that all these factors contribute to life but isn’t sufficiently describing the whole process of life. Of course, it’s also worth noting that this brief definition is definitely not sufficient to describe life from all angles, and is subject to scrutiny, but let’s just say that I put it this way to take our discussion just one step further and build on top of it (+ I think a scientific definition, something in the line of  “metabolistic creatures” would be quite confusing in our context, especially that we are talking about extra-terrestrial life. <br></p><h3 id="But-wait-how-can-we-know-if-something-is-alive-or-not-if-our-definitions-of-this-thing-actually-vary-widely"><a href="#But-wait-how-can-we-know-if-something-is-alive-or-not-if-our-definitions-of-this-thing-actually-vary-widely" class="headerlink" title="But wait, how can we know if something is alive or not if our definitions of this thing actually vary widely?"></a>But wait, how can we know if something is alive or not if our definitions of this thing actually vary widely?</h3><p>Do definitions give us an entitlement to actually measure something? can defining money be enough to measure it ? Well, we need something like counting the money in order to actually operate with it. And life also needs the same approach, so how can we actually measure if something is alive ? Let’s first think of what level of abstraction we want to operate with in this context of measuring, because after all biological entities (organisms) can actually be described with regards to Physics, Chemistry, or Biology, it’s just up to how we choose to describe it, where we want to play with these descriptions, and how complex we want our description to be. Let’s try to think about describing it on every level possible, and come out with a fair approach.</p><p>From a biology perspective, how can we measure it ? Well, there are probably a ton of ways in principle that will lead to the differentiation of alive and lifeless entities by way of Biology, examples include looking at a sample under a microscope and detecting cells or enzymes (which will take us back to our definition of life by necessity of cells and enzymes), but this can be applied in a terrestrial context, in which life as we know it is actually extremely abundant. But how can we apply this extremely specific paradigm to our fellow extra-terrestrial life ? can we build on top of this assumption to detect life outside earth? what if alive entities outside earth don’t actually operate with similar “biology”? </p><p>So one alternative approach is to get down one level of abstraction and look at life from the perspective of Chemistry, and this requires some kind of stripping down of the organism to the chemical level, and one of the great theories responsible for this kind of approach is called assembly theory. So assembly theory is very interesting because it solves the problem we put forward above, which is that because this theory deals with the chemical “atoms” of organisms, it is irrelevant what “kind of life” they posses (or what type of life&#x2F;technology created them), whether they have our “cells” or any other possible type of a functional unit, and by extension gives us a way to approach even extra-terrestrial life. But the difficulty to determine whether that unit is alive or not still remains with us even when looking at it from a Chemistry perspective, so how does assembly theory deal with this ? let’s try building some concepts of assembly theory using the following bullet points and see where we go from there: 1) Assembly theory deals with the number of steps needed to reconstruct any given molecule, and let’s call the number of shortest steps needed to reconstruct a molecule (assembly index). For example, if we take this in the world of words and say we have the word ‘assassin’, assume we want to break it apart, now to reconstruct it, we first create the ‘a’ , ’s’, ’s’ individually, so now for the second syllable we can reuse the syllable ‘ass’ and add it with one step by reusing it, and then we can finally conclude with the ‘i’ and ’n’, giving us in total 6 steps of the shortest path.</p><p>Ok, so how can this be useful to our context?<br>2) Since it deals with the number of steps to reconstruct a molecule, the authors of the theory have detected that the number of steps needed to reconstruct a deconstructed molecule in the lab, and the “liveliness” of a molecule are probabilistically proportional i.e. the more steps needed to construct the molecule using the shortest path,<br>the more the probability that it has been constructed by a biological process or itself a biological entity. 3) It was a small lie when I said that assembly theory deals with “life” directly, rather,  assembly theory actually tells us what process probabilistically (information-guided or not) led to “life” (or lack thereof), and not really what life is, in some sense. Fundamentally, what assembly theory tells us is that this studied object&#x2F;molecule was most-likely created (or not created in the case of abiotic molecules&#x2F;objects) with an information-guided “plan” (and the only two processes we can describe as information-guided include biological and technological). In the case of biology, the information comes from genes, and in the case of technology the information comes from other “intelligent” beings. You can think of this biological&#x2F;technological duality as one “sacrifice” that we had to make when leaving the realm of investigating strictly biologically and entering the world of chemical investigation (although am not really sure if this is actually a compromise because I can think of it as an advantage, but it’s for sure one way to put it in mind) 4) If you’re curious on what’s the number of steps (assembly index) used as a cut-point to differentiate an information process going on “under the hood” in assembly theory or not, it’s ~15 steps and more that indicates that this molecule was probabilistically an information guided molecule, according to a 2.5 million database of molecules studied.</p><p>As with regards to Physics, which is our most fundamental description, life probably wouldn’t hold a <b>practically</b> detectable fundamental difference that is useful to approach in this context.<br><br></p><h3 id="What-about-other-signs-of-life-if-any"><a href="#What-about-other-signs-of-life-if-any" class="headerlink" title="What about other signs of life, if any?"></a>What about other signs of life, if any?</h3><p>Of course, assembly theory is one indicator of life, but there are plenty of other potential signs that could help us in identifying “footsteps” of biological phenomena. Some of those signs include gaseous biosignatures, which are gases that potentially arise as a result of biological phenomena. detection of gases like oxygen or methane in certain amounts are usually correlated with the existence of biological life. Another type of biosignature is the temporal biosignature, which includes changes in potential environmental factors at certain times that can be traced back to biological phenomena. An example includes fluctuations in carbon dioxide concentrations during different seasons due to increased or decreased consumptions by biological systems (you can think of this specific example as an extension of gaseous biosignatures in some sense). Other indicators of life include the lack of chemical equilibrium, known as chemical disequilibrium, which has been observed in earth’s atmosphere (since life is abundant on earth, a correlation has been made based on other details). A good example of this is the lack of oxidization of CH4 and O2 to CO2 and H2O, which is actually considered as a sign&#x2F;indicator of life or a biosignature. However, these indicators are all potential ones, and not definitive ones because they are subject to false positives, since some can be explained with regards to abiotic phenomena. So taking the context when finding these biosignatures and weighing it with other evidence is pretty crucial to come with relatively conclusive answers on the validity of these biosignatures. But up until this point, conclusive answers with regards to biological life hasn’t been achieved regarding those biosignatures or other signs, but will probably actualise in the near future since projects and missions have been initiated in line of these investigations.</p><h3 id="UFOs"><a href="#UFOs" class="headerlink" title="UFOs:"></a>UFOs:</h3><p>So since we have discussed some tools to detect life, this <b>possible</b> evidence here known as UFOs is somehow different than all other evidences&#x2F;signs of life because its possible significance might take us to the leap not only of life, but also of intelligent life too. UFOs are Unidentified Flying Objects in the sky that have an ambiguity in their explanation to the observers. Initially, all “weird” phenomena in the sky have the possibility of being called a UFO by different people, but can be deemed as an identified object (or known physical phenomena) if given enough investigation whether by governments or individuals. UFO’s has been reported by people looking at the sky or taking footage of some unfamiliar type of sighting in the sky, and also has been reported by pilots, and some have actually experienced a near-hit with their planes with those unidentified objects. Some of those objects, in fact a good portion of them, turned out to be something that’s not out of the familiar when given proper investigation, but a small portion remains “unidentified” even after investigation. One investigation that might reflect to us the proper validity of the UFO phenomena as a sign of extra-terrestrial life is from the french government, and they published data with regards to the UFOs claims and footage from people, and what they came up with reflects the true significance of these sightings, and this following graph shows what each of these reports from people corresponds in a category of validity:<br><img src="/img/al1.jpeg" alt="Courtsey of &lt;a href= &quot;https://www.cnes-geipan.fr/en&quot; style=color:darkblue;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt;"> </p><hr>The 3.3% of the category D is what might be a significant observation in our search for extra-terrestrial life for now, which, I think, holds a Non-zero probability for their existence in this discussion.<h3 id="Final-Scrabbles-on-life-outside-earth"><a href="#Final-Scrabbles-on-life-outside-earth" class="headerlink" title="Final Scrabbles on life outside earth:"></a>Final Scrabbles on life outside earth:</h3><p>It seems to me that we are getting closer and closer to finding better tools to actually begin to detect life extra-terrestrially. It might seem like the most important factor is just the mere thought&#x2F;philosophy of existence of life outside earth, but actually from the perspective we see today, the most important, crucial , and exciting part is our ability to actually detect those things if we have the ability to encounter such systems. And there is a possibility that what made earth the only place with life on it in all history until this point, is that we were too “blind” to actually see anything outside.</p><br><span class="material-icons">subdirectory_arrow_right</span> This specific topic has actually changed some of my perspectives on probabilities in general, and how to assess them. Try to write or think about this aspect of the argument and see where you go from there.]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Quasi-victims of Words?</title>
    <link href="/2022/04/22/words/"/>
    <url>/2022/04/22/words/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so Let’s back-track to the most fundamental layers of language, so languages contain the grammar layer and labels&#x2F;words&#x2F;meanings layer (essentially sentax and semantics). Not to bash the syntax&#x2F;grammar, but today we’ll focus on semantics or meanings. This topic is so interesting because our thoughts are actually conveyed through these meanings of words. It could be argued that language is the building block of thoughts. So today just like I am semi-obsessed with definitions, I’ll try to pass that torch in some way and show their importance from one angle. The way I like to think about words and meanings&#x2F;definitions is that words are the tip of the iceberg, and the definitions are the part of the iceberg that’s under the water. In this analogy, the underlying process of definitions is inherently much more vague than the word itself because it’s basically under the water, you don’t see it when using the word (at least not as vivid as the word itself).  And this takes us to another point which is that it might seem like definitions are the only representation of words, but in reality there a whole lots of other things affecting the interpretation by us of that word, and an example of such other representations is the context where the word is most used can be representative of it when it’s not really an objective factor of the word. To let the point drive home, let’s track down how a word is acquired in someone’s vocabulary and see where it takes us from there. Let’s take the word bias, so most probably the track of how the word was acquired is that the person gained recognition of the word when reading or listening to the word somewhere, then a little dictionary lookup (or physical dictionaries i.e. other humans) probably sufficed with nailing the word and using it and interpreting it in a certain way. Now let’s see how this might actualise in practice. Imagine if that same person one day had an idea to start a project, but before he does so, he tries to take some opinions of some people around him. So one guy he talked to told him that he thinks that this idea is bound to fail because he believes that the idea arose as a result of  confirmation “bias” (assuming the advisor knows the project starter really well to give that judgement), in the sense that he’s just trying to confirm his ideas of demand with the project, and as a result, people will probably not be attracted to that type of project. Now, let’s analyze the criticism with regards to what it actually means. So bias is a systematic error in one’s reasoning (error just means that a relative mistake has been done, relative to normative models of rationality). Now once we dig deeper into the meaning, we see that it doesn’t really tell us something profound about the project’s success, it’s basically saying that the ideas with which the project was constructed are fallible relative to some model, and after thinking about the meaning of this word, it makes the leap to say that failure will arise as a result of “bias” much harder and questionable because mistakes in ideas we construct are usually assumed as a necessity and is not an excuse to say that something will “probably fail”. Now, I think that if we haven’t thought about the definition in this example, the leap to say that the project will fail is much easier because of other attachments to words like the contexts they are most used in or the psychological attachment that societies associate with. Of course, The probability of failure is still there even after interpretation, and the criticism still holds, but it just made the picture much more clear with regards to our context when we opened the word for reinterpretation. The example might not be the most realistic one, but I am saying this to say that sometimes words get misinterpreted and confuse things because they are subject to a lot of emotional and contextual load which might obsecure their real meaning that’s behind that word&#x2F;words. And we tend to assume the meanings of words in a lot of contexts, but actually sometimes thinking deeply about their actual meanings brushes a lot of confusion off.</p><p><b>If I had to write this blog post with one description, it would be Activation of bear mode in this image:</b><br><img src="/img/img1.JPG" ></p><p>It might seem from the previous example that I am stressing on the questioning of meanings when they’re received or given from&#x2F;to the outside world (i.e. conversations), but the core idea here is to really question the fabric of your thoughts through words even when you’re just talking to yourself or introspecting. On the other hand, it’s pretty easy to overlearn this in some sense, I mean it would be impractical to consciously question a word like “food” in every context we are trying to use it in or hear it, for example. At the end of the day we are limited by bounded rationality in some contexts, which is just how we operate through ideas with limited time, information, and cognitive load at the time of processing things. Going down a hole trying to define every word used&#x2F;heard&#x2F;read can get counter-productive real quick in some contexts, but what can be a healthy approach is when you find yourself confused or semi-confused about some conclusion or just trying to understand an idea&#x2F;ideas, trying not to go too far with assumptions you’re building on (i.e. questioning words being used) might be a good idea. And this might seem trivial because how can a word be used without knowing its meaning? Well, you’ll be surprised how much the mind conflicts some things if not consciously thought through. + I can see it being easier to question what words are next to each other, rather than question the word’s meaning itself. </p><p>Let’s try to visualise an approach towards words and definitions with some toy I came across. So this is the default shape of this toy:<br><img src="/img/img2.jpg" style=width:95%;></p><p>Now imagine that each cell in that grid&#x2F;toy represents a word you’re using in a conversation, whether with yourself or with someone else (assume it’s an intellectual one rather than a casual one).</p><p>So having shown our grid&#x2F;toy, we’ll now try to represent with each cell (or hypothetical word as we mentioned) how well we know the meanings of words we are using in our hypothetical convo in these following three states:<br><img src="/img/img11.JPG"></p><p><b>State 1 &#x3D; You know the meaning of the word really well, objectively.</p><p>State 1&#x2F;2: You know the meaning of the word, but if you just scratch a deeper layer you’ll probably find yourself confused. </p><p>State 0 &#x3D; You have no idea what that word means.</b></p><hr><img src="/img/img3.jpg" ><br><br>Now this is one final arbitrary probability I can see ending up being used in an intellectual convo (for both parties each, if more than one person is present), on average of course. And Probably one thing I can see getting out all of this is to actually try to see what probability of state 1’s and state 1/2's you experience in your thoughts or conversations with constant reflection. It might seem like a non-demanding task on first sight, but distinguishing state 1’s and state 1/2’s can actually be difficult. A state 1/2 is a disguised state 1 on first sight, but is nothing near a state 1 after thinking it through. So it’s all a matter of perspective and relativity in some sense.<p><br><br>Speaking of clarity of words, the clarity of terms used in the sciences (or at least the trial to do so) and other intellectual endeavours is one aspect that makes them truly special and productive. I mean in the context of science usually when we are talking about definitions: 1) Terms are agreed upon their definitions clearly without confusion e.g. gravity, 2) debated upon their definition e.g. wars, or 3) the definitions are being built with empirical evidence and experiments e.g. consciousness. Of course all of these defnitions can exist in more than one of those categories and is not an either&#x2F;or, but the state of these endevours is probably something to take notes from and try to build in our own scheme in some way.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chaos around us?</title>
    <link href="/2022/03/26/us/"/>
    <url>/2022/03/26/us/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When we think of everything around us, it seems very intuitive to say that “minor” tweaks in initial inputs or conditions usually lead to just tiny little changes <span id="more"></span>  in the output or macro-response we get. And this is not coming completely out of the blue, but rather this at first sight seems consistent because many times we don’t dig enough to see the consequences of things&#x2F;inputs really precisely, so we deem it as insignificant because it wasn’t detected thoroughly in the first place. And the leap to generalize this observation is not a really big one if overlooking </p><p> detailed actualisation of say our behavior is common, to some   extent. But all these assumptions were questioned head-on when chaos theory came to be around the 1960’s. So when we are talking about chaos theory (or chaotic systems) what we are saying essentially is that when a certain system just changes its initial conditions slightly, and when I say slightly I am talking one decimal number in a system, the whole system can completely change its behavior given some time (the decimal number is just an abstract representation of something real, a temperature in a certain place, for example). Chaos comes from the fundamental dependence on initial conditions of the system, and what I mean by that is if you imagine an infinite number that represents say the wobble of a hypothetical object (3.2539853…), no matter how much you walk through that infinite number, all infinite digits of this system are extremely relevant to its final behavior (or its wobble in this case).</p><p> Let’s take an example of a chair orientation in a university’s interview location. Imagine if the orientation of a waiting-room chair outside the interview room was situated in a way that faces other people&#x2F;students who are being interviewed through a glass. </p><p> Then at the end of the first interview, the first interviewer fist pumps the first interviewee (assume we live in a world where a fist pump is an extremely accepting gesture). It seems like this “initial condition” of say the chair orientation facing the glass won’t yield any big difference in students in the waiting rooms entering,<br> quitting&#x2F;leaving, or getting stressed for this competitive position of choosing one person, but we can infer from the behavior of chaotic systems&#x2F;chaos theory that if we just change initial conditions i.e. chair orientation in this example, it might actually make a student enter, leave, be more competent for the interview, by extension alter the chance of the student entering the university, and one step further, change whole experiences that would shape this person in a certain way. Had we changed the orientation of this chair say opposite to the glass showing his peers being interviewed (or remove the glass), we would have had a completely different Ahmad, for example. This might be a slightly misrepresenting example, and not necessarily a clear-cut “chaotic system”, but the analogy that might help here is thinking of the chair orientation as a very small decimal place, say the 8 in this number 1.9264257258 that represents Ahmad’s life, for example, and if we change that 8 to say a 1 (i.e the chair orientation) it might look trivial to the change it might yield in Ahmad’s “life”, but we have come to know through studying chaotic systems that it’s actually not that trivial to how these small “conditions” add up in the final output after all. </p><p>  To touch base on the status quo, the weather is a very good example of chaotic systems (real ones, unlike the above example), specifically deterministic chaotic system. So if we choose to divide these words into two parts, what we mean by the deterministic part of it is that the system’s state is limited to a certain kind of behavior, in other words,<br>  we don’t seem to see rocks raining from the sky in the case of weather, but when we are talking about the chaotic part of the word, we mean that there is a fundamental limitation to tackle the system’s precision to its core, so we deem it as chaotic because of the inherent “unpredictability”. So to put the two words together again we can describe it as: the inherent unpredictability of a system within its limited bounds of behavior.<br>  So if we bring an alien species that look at the weather from the outside, and can calculate the digits of all the variables in the weather system to infinity (whatever that means), then the system wouldn’t be “chaotic” in our interpretation of the word. The way Ed Lorenz, a Meteorologist came across chaotic systems was indeed through trying to predict atmospheric patterns. So he ran a simulation on a computer with 12 different variables of the weather like the temperature and other related ones. After the first simulation was run,<br>  he wanted to run it again, but instead of entering all digits from the beginning of the first simulation again, he started from the middle of it to save time, and the digits in the second simulation were entered to 3 decimal places (0.345) rather than the six decimal places (0.345212) in the first simulation, and the final output of the second simulation was completely different from the first simulation due to this discrepancy.<br>    <img src="/img/Untitled3.png" style=width:95%; /></p><p>   “Sensitive dependence on initial conditions”, the words just seem like an intuitive and clear set of strings at first sight, like I can imagine myself saying to a person living prior to the explorations of chaos theory that certain systems are “sensitively dependent on their initial conditions” and a reaction that might be expected (maybe naively expected) is: “of course some things ‘sensitively depend’ on their first conditions, what are they dependent on other than that?” It’s almost like these words don’t really show the size of the conclusions, but to put it another way, let’s just say that after the explorations of chaos theory we came to know that some systems really really really sensitively depend on their initial conditions (we are talking infinitely sensitive here).  To put all of this into perspective, different systems’ “chaos” differ from one system to another. </p><p> Some are extremely chaotic systems, and others are less chaotic i.e. easily predictable. Each system seems to follow a certain kind of “attractor”, which is an abstract representation of states where a system seems to follow or emerge towards. These attractors can give us an indication of how chaotic a system is, and give us hints on it’s predictability as well.</p><ul><li>(More on attractors and the mathematics behind chaos theory  in this amazing <a href="https://youtu.be/uzJXeluCKMs">video</a>).</li></ul>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>Who is behind the wheel?</title>
    <link href="/2022/03/08/firb/"/>
    <url>/2022/03/08/firb/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are the motivators behind our behavior some kind of crystal-clear variables that we see clearly on introspection? Well, due to the magnitude and temporal-limitations of our behavior motivators sometimes, It’s hard to know what drives the behavior we did or intend to do. There is such a wide-variety of inputs we derive our behaviors from that sometimes it’s easy to lose track of all the mechanisms behind these behaviors (That’s why game theory is there to somwhat help us with this). In one way, the “who is behind the wheel” analogy is a fallacious one because it assumes that the behavior driver and the behavior doer are two separate things, but a lot of the times the behavior doer and the behavior mechanisms are just one part of the same mesh i.e. us. But I am happy to stick with the analogy here because I think it’s good to strip away the behavior motivators from the doer, and then after examining it abstractly, we can re-embed it into the behavior doer and see how it weighs in with the other factors. </p><p>When we are talking about these variables, what kind of things are we talking about ? One way I thought about it is to separate these motivators into psychological ones and reasoning ones. So by psychological ones, I mean the behavior motivators that actually push one to behave a certain way due to first-person subjective experiences, like emotions. Reasoning ones fall under the tendency towards a behavior due to leaning towards logic&#x2F;thinking, like weighing pros and cons of an experience, for example. It might be that this is actually a false dichotomy, and it turns out to be lots of other “types”, but I think a good portion of these motivators fall in one way or another under these two umbrellas.</p><hr><p>But are these two separate from each other after we apply them to a non-abstract realistic context? One thing to put in mind is that factors lying under those two types are dependent variables in the loose sense of the term. An example of that would be the ability of our subjective emotions to somewhat skew our “logical analysis” into one way rather than another. </p><p>Taking this a step further, let’s try examining the behavior of Adolf Hitler in the context of killing the Jews. When he thought that he had the right to kill people of a certain group, what was actually wrong with this type of behavior from the inside perspective i.e. the motivators of his behaviors ? From one angle, I see it as fundamentally a lack of well-prioritized behavior drivers in the context of his leadership. What I mean by this is that he prioritized the state of him having the right to kill a certain group of people (for whatever reason), rather than prioritize the idea that he might be wrong about the fate of those people (you can think of this sentence as describing an egoistic approach). The morals, specific historical context, other many specific factors can be for another day, but hopefully we can see how one aspect of the systematic structure of a behavior can actually unravel some aspects of its origins, in one way.</p><p>When it comes to experiences, I tend to think it’s useful to evaluate what’s pushing us towards going through a certain experience or towards avoiding it, even if it seems obvious that it’s the “right” thing to do. For example, if we take “comfort zones” (whatever that means), and say that a person’s “comfort” lies within a certain limit in a social context e.g. comfortable not approaching people. This comfort the person has built can actually skew ones career goals ,for example, towards being inside this “comfort zone”, if that makes sense.  So in this example the “comfort zone” might be put as a priority subconsciously rather than a certain career goal, which might at one point lead the person to actually change their career goals to “good enough” rather than “great” just to encompass his&#x2F;her experiences within the boundaries of this psychological status i.e. comfort zone (the good&#x2F;great scale here is the person’s actual desire if the “comfort zone” was absent).</p><p>To make it more vivid, let’s check out a semi-visual depiction of the process of enacting in a certain behavior&#x2F;experience in two drawings I drew, which compares two types of approaches towards an experience or behavior in a crude way. When behavior goes to become an automated process:<br><img src="/img/Untitled1.png" /></p><p>Trial to optimize by passing the behavior through a “filter” i.e. constant recognition of behavior drivers:<br><img src="/img/Untitled2.jpeg" /></p><p>I think I have stressed the structure of enacting in different kinds of behaviors here because I think the chances of going “autopilot” are much more when priorities&#x2F;structures of our behavior stimulators are not known consciously. When “autopilot” is on, I believe it’s hard to ever feel any slap in the face that life tends to give us sometimes. And I think it’s necessary to be able to take&#x2F;detect those slaps, and harness something out of that energy.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Philosophy</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
